<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A rejoinder consisting of two parts, the first entituled, The ballance, or, A vindication of the proceedings and judgement of Parliament and their ministers, in the cases of William (called lord) Craven, Christopher Love. : From the scandalous allegations and ironical reflections of Ralph Farmer ... in a late infamous libel of his, named, The imposter dethron'd, etc. ... Wherein the Commonwealth's case as to the one is briefly stated, and the treasons of the other are rehearsed as a looking-glass for the priests, and an awakening to England. : The second, Evil scattered from the throne, and the wheel brought over the wicked: in an examination of that part of The imposter dethron'd as is in way of reply to The throne of truth exalted, etc.</title>
            <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3004A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170664</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504319</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504319</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76759)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2581:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A rejoinder consisting of two parts, the first entituled, The ballance, or, A vindication of the proceedings and judgement of Parliament and their ministers, in the cases of William (called lord) Craven, Christopher Love. : From the scandalous allegations and ironical reflections of Ralph Farmer ... in a late infamous libel of his, named, The imposter dethron'd, etc. ... Wherein the Commonwealth's case as to the one is briefly stated, and the treasons of the other are rehearsed as a looking-glass for the priests, and an awakening to England. : The second, Evil scattered from the throne, and the wheel brought over the wicked: in an examination of that part of The imposter dethron'd as is in way of reply to The throne of truth exalted, etc.</title>
                  <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 86 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons, at the Bull and Mouth neer Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: p. 19-21 numbered 61, 26-27; p. 24-25 numbered 30-31.</note>
                  <note>Incomplete? Catchword "THE" at foot of p. 86.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Craven, William Craven, --  Earl of, 1606-1697.</term>
               <term>Love, Christopher, 1618-1651.</term>
               <term>Farmer, Ralph. --  Imposter dethron'd, or, The Quakers throne of truth detected to bee Satans seat of lyes.</term>
               <term>Imposter dethron'd, or, The Quakers throne of truth detected to bee Satans seat of lyes.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171621:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A REJOINDER Conſiſting of <hi>TWO PARTS,</hi> The <hi>FIRST</hi> entituled, The BALLANCE, OR, A VINDICATION OF The <hi>Proceedings</hi> and <hi>Judgement</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> and their <hi>Ministers,</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>In the caſes of</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>WILLIAM</hi> (called Lord) <hi>CRAVEN,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHRISTOPHER LOVE.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>From the ſcandalous <hi>Allegations,</hi> and Ironical <hi>Reflections</hi> of <hi>RALPH FARMER,</hi> (a pretended Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Briſtol)</hi> in a late infamous Libel of his, named, <hi>The Impoſtor Dethron'd, &amp;c.</hi> Dedicated to the Former.</p>
            <p>Wherein the <hi>Commonwealth's</hi> Caſe as to the <hi>One</hi> is briefly ſtated, and the <hi>Treaſons</hi> of the <hi>Other</hi> are rehearſed as a <hi>LOOKING-GLASS</hi> for the PRIESTS, and an AWAKENING to <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond, EVIL ſcattered from the THRONE, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> WHEEL brought over the WICKED: In an EXAMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NATION of that part of the <hi>Impoſtor Dethron'd,</hi> as is in way of <hi>Reply</hi> to the <hi>Throne of Truth exalted, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>GEORGE BISHOP.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that is firſt in his own caſe ſeemeth juſt, but his Neighb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r cometh and ſearcheth him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the Bull and Mouth neer <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1658.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171621:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171621:2"/>
            <head>To <hi>the ſober</hi> READER.</head>
            <p>TO ſhorten the enſuing Vindication, and to give thee more perfectly to underſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the ground of the Conteſt between <hi>Ralph Farmer</hi> and my ſelfe, I deſire thee to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that it was not on my part; for though he gave me many provocations, (who had not done him any wrong) yet I began not with him, but rather choſe to abide in ſilence, (knowing the man) then to have to do with ſuch a one, <hi>The beginning of the words of whoſe mouth is fooliſhneſs, and the end of whoſe talk is miſchievous madneſs, as Solomon</hi> ſaith of the fool, Eccl. 10. 13.</p>
            <p>And in the ſame purpoſe of mind I determined to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, had he not in his Narrative of J. N's coming into <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol, &amp;c.</hi> charged the blasphemies [there] affirmed, upon the truth of the living God, and the many thouſands of the friends thereof in this Nation, ſcornfully called Quakers; and <hi>me</hi> in particular with matter of fact, as to my publique Truſt, which with more then ordinary Care, Hazard, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, I have a witneſs in my conſcience as well as amongſt men, to have honeſtly diſcharged.</p>
            <p>In all which knowing the truth, and thoſe people and my ſelf to be innocent; and being aſſured that a principal cauſe of his vilifying of me was <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> his Letter, ſent unto and taken upon <hi>J. N.</hi> (wherein the ſpirit that then led him &amp; that compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and their actions, was judged and denyed) which being wrote with my hand, he expected would be made uſe of, and my Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony therein for the clearing of thoſe people from his ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous imputations of deteſtableneſs and biaſphemy; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſible that the great deſign of the Devil in all, was to diſ-ſavor truth, and to make it abhorr'd with thoſe to whom the Relation ſhould come; I was preſſed in ſpirit (being a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol</hi> during the time of this tranſaction, and well inform'd in the truth of the particulars) to make anſwer thereunto, (not
<pb facs="tcp:171621:3"/> purpoſely in reference to my own particular, as if I were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, but) for the clearing of the truth, that all who would, might ſee it free of the monſtrous apparel in which he had clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed it, and that thoſe that ſhould notwithſtanding ſhut their eyes, might be left without excuſe in the day that God ſhall judge the ſecrets of all hearts by the man Chriſt Jeſus: And that my Anſwer I ſtiled as it was, viz. <hi>The Throne of Truth exalted over the Powers of darkneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whereunto he being conſtrained to give up the Cauſe, and being ſorely plagu'd and tormented therewith, and at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his wickedneſs, he not onely falls upon me with all the rancor lodged within his malicious breaſt, but having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed the earth, and rummag'd thorough the unclean bowels of the Nation, and conſulted with his black Generation, he grovels up into his bottomleſs pit what falſe reports he could meet with among the Enemies of the State and Truth, and having in his firſt ſeventeen pages bid defiance to Perfection, (the work of the Miniſtry for which <hi>Chriſt gave gifts unto men when he aſcended up on high)</hi> and to thoſe who are made clean by the <hi>Eternal Word, the blood of the New Covenant which cleanſeth from [all] ſin, (Chriſt Jeſus the light of the World, that lighteth every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the World) and to converſion from evil,</hi> as of the <hi>Devil,</hi> (to ſhew himſelf whoſe Miniſter he is) he caſts up all again at me from the depths of darkneſs, in the following 100. pages, the whole of his Book, which he calls (ſuch is the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency of the heat, of his ſcorched Tongue) <hi>The Impoſtor Dethron'd,</hi> (who is proved to be the man) <hi>Or, The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Throne of Truth detected to be Satans Seat of Lyes:</hi> (which is not true of it, but is true of himſelf and his generation) <hi>By way of Reply to a quaking railing Pamphlet written by Capt. Biſhop,</hi> (The ſlanders are his own, the Truth is mine.) <hi>entituled, The Throne of Truth exalted over the powers of darkneſs;</hi> (So it is, and ſo it ſhall ſtand over his head for ever;) <hi>wherein is briefly hinted the rottenneſs of the Quakers Converſion and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in general,</hi> (It's the ſtate of his own ſtock, whoſe root is rottenneſs, and whoſe bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me is going up as the duſt,
<pb facs="tcp:171621:3"/> not of thoſe people whoſe Rock is the Stone of Iſrael.) <hi>Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified in this buſie Biſhop;</hi> (The buſie Biſhop appears to be himſelf in the behalf of theſe mens Treaſons; what I did was in diſcharge of my Truſt) <hi>In ſpecial inſtanced in his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices againſt the Eſtate of the Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>Life of Mr.</hi> Love; (The one adjudged by the Parliament, the other by their High Court of Juſtice, and my duty faithfully done in both, long before I knew the thing that is reproach't a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.) <hi>By occaſion whereof this Truth is aſſerted,</hi> viz. <hi>Jf we may judge of the Conſcience, Honeſty, and Perfection of quakers in general by this man in particular, a man may be as vile a perſon as any under Heaven, and yet a perfect Quaker.</hi> Which being proved a Lye both in ground and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, this is affirmed of a truth, &amp; made good, viz, That if the conſcience, honeſty &amp; profeſſion of the Miniſters of England in general, may be judged by Ralph Farmer, [and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he writes] in particular, a man may be one of the vileſt of mer, yea, a notorious Traytor, and yet a profeſſed Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>This is the ſumme of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>number of its Name,</hi> with which, <hi>as a Servant to the State,</hi> I am now to encounter, like as I anſwered the Narrative <hi>as a friend of Truth,</hi> unto which I ſhall preſently apply my ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Briſtol <date>the <hi>13th.</hi> day of the <hi>11th.</hi> Month, 1657.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>G. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:171621:4"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171621:4"/>
            <head>THE BALLANCE, OR, A VINDICATION, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I come to any <hi>new</hi> Engagement, it is requiſite that I firſt ſtate the <hi>old,</hi> and briefly shew what hath already <hi>been,</hi> and how it is <hi>now;</hi> and wherein a <hi>Reply</hi> is hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto declin'd.</p>
            <p>The great <hi>Queſtion</hi> or <hi>Cauſe</hi> in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie between <hi>Ralph Farmer</hi> and <hi>my ſelfe,</hi> (in his <note n="*" place="margin">Sata<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thron'd.</note> 
               <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative,</hi> and my <hi>Anſwer</hi> thereunto) was this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viz. Whether</hi> J. N. <hi>and thoſe with him (as to his coming to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Throne of Truth, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Briſtol, and what was done to him by them) and the people cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led QUAKERS, were one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> he affirmed, and for <hi>this</hi> purpoſe published his <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Satan.</hi> Title page, &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part, &amp;c. <hi>Impoſtor, p:</hi> 24: <hi>Throne,</hi> firſt ten pages.</note> and call'd it <hi>Quakeriſme in its exaltation;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded what he had ſaid of the <hi>one,</hi> upon the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I denyed, and proved by plain demonſtration, and full teſtimony of <hi>Truth,</hi> (which shall ſtand for ever) That they were not <hi>one,</hi> not led by <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> ſpirit, but ſeen (to be <hi>gone</hi> forth) and <hi>judged,</hi> and <hi>denyed,</hi> and the ſpirit that led them, long before their coming thither; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, That thoſe <hi>people,</hi> and the <hi>truth</hi> they witneſs, were <hi>clear,</hi> and <hi>unconcerned;</hi> and that his <hi>Narrative,</hi> and its <note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Title, Deſign</hi> of it, and <hi>End, Foundation,</hi> and <hi>Matter</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained (ſo far as it related unto them, whom, and their <hi>faith</hi> he had taken that occaſion highly to charge, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, and abuſe) was a Lye.</p>
            <p>For the clearing of this (being the <hi>Axis,</hi> or that on which the weight of the whole did hang) I expected [when
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171621:5"/> I heard of his <hi>Reply]</hi> him to have ſpoken (had he any thing to ſay) but when I had view'd it round, I found the <hi>field</hi> quitted, and the <hi>Cauſe</hi> left me without an Engagement.</p>
            <p>The next <hi>thing</hi> in diſpute, was his <hi>Narrative, Whether it was a true Relation, or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A true Narrative and Relation</hi> it is, ſaith he in his Title-Page; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Satan.</hi> Title-page. Epiſtle.</note> and in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Reader</hi> he pledgeth for it his <hi>faithful Aſſurance</hi> in theſe words, <hi>But this I can, and do faithfully aſſure you, That there is nothing here of the one, or the other, but what is real truth, as will be made good upon any occaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[Then which, What higher <hi>Engagement</hi> can there be of <hi>honesty</hi> to induce a belief, for which end it is held forth?]</p>
            <p>It is not ſo, <hi>(replyed I)</hi> for the <hi>examination</hi> of <hi>one</hi> of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Throne.</hi> p. 29, 30.</note> them, which gives the lye to his <hi>Concluſion,</hi> upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſal of their <hi>Papers</hi> and <hi>Examinations,</hi> he hath wholly left out. <note place="margin">Pag. 30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That Paſſage of the <hi>Examination</hi> of a <hi>ſecond,</hi> which <hi>checks</hi> the <hi>deſign</hi> and <hi>drift</hi> of his <hi>Relation,</hi> he hath ommit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <note place="margin">Pag. 28, 29.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Examination</hi> of a <hi>third</hi> he hath affirmed to <hi>ſay,</hi> and produced to prove (contrary to his own <hi>Record</hi> of his ſaid <hi>Examination)</hi> that which it <hi>ſaith not.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 26, 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>All the contents of a <hi>fourth</hi> Paper he hath neither repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, (though ſhort) nor in the very words (which <hi>clear</hi> the matter) but makes up a <hi>pack</hi> of his own, and then preſents it as the <hi>language</hi> of the Paper, to ſlander the innocent. <note place="margin">Pag. 27, 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A fifth <hi>Depoſition</hi> he brings forth <hi>clipt</hi> of that clauſe, which renders it <hi>falſe ſworn.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pa. 2 5, 7, 8. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And a ſixth Letter wanting divers words, and a material part of a ſentence; and in the cloſe, changed from its own, into ſuch an expreſſion <hi>(forged</hi> in, and then pointed to with a marginal Note, <hi>OBSE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>VE)</hi> as not onely quite altered the ſenſe, but rendred it very ſcandalous, and the life of him liable to danger, had it really been his, whoſe was the ſubſcription. <note place="margin">Pag. 25, 31, 32</note>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon I concluded his <hi>Narrative a lye,</hi> and him as a <hi>Narrator reprobate to faith and honesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171621:5"/>
            <p> Of this (being the <hi>hinge</hi> on which turned the whole of his Reputation, as on the other did the <hi>Cauſe)</hi> I liſtened for a thorough Vindication (could he have made it) but throughout the whole Reply I could not hear a <hi>whisper</hi> of his ſaid <hi>Engagement</hi> in his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> nor of the words, <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate to faith and honeſty;</hi> Nor of his <hi>quotations</hi> of his own <note place="margin">Pag 74.</note> books, which I had charged upon him to have made to <hi>belye</hi> one another, and both to give himſelf the <hi>lye,</hi> and to prove him a <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> in ſuch a buſineſs of conſequence as <hi>foreſeeing</hi> and <hi>foretelling</hi> things to come, of which he ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vaunted: No nor of, nor to my demands, <hi>viz. By what ſpirit didſt thou foreſee, and foretel? The infallib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſpirit thou haſt not, ſo thou hast confeſſed, pag.</hi> 34. <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the ſpirit of the Lord is infallible. Is it not the Witch, the fallible ſpirit that is out of the truth, that hath divined? ſeeing that ſpirit that doth foretell, which is not the ſpirit of the Lord, is ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then I conſidered him as to <hi>Religion,</hi> and I found (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it upon him by plain Scripture) That <hi>his ſhare in</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 61, 62, 63, 70, 71.</note> 
               <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity he had renounc't.</hi> That his [<note n="b" place="margin">Pag. 61.</note>] <hi>hopes</hi> to be ſaved, his [<note n="c" place="margin">Pag. 65, 66.</note>] <hi>happineſs,</hi> and <hi>way</hi> to true happineſs, was a lye; and that his [<note n="d" place="margin">Pag. 63, 64, 65.</note>] <hi>Miniſters, Miniſtry, Word, Churches, Unity, Orders, Peace, Civility, good Manners,</hi> &amp; <hi>all [that] Religion</hi> which he ſaith <hi>Apollion &amp; Abaddon the deſtroyer is tearing, laying waſte, and confounding is the ſame; for all that is confounding, tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and laying waſte,</hi> (and he ſaith <hi>the</hi> [<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Satan.</hi> Epiſt. to the Reader</note>] <hi>deſtroyer is tearing, laying waſt, &amp; confounding miniſters, miniſtry, Word, Churches, Unity, Order, Peace Civility, good Manners, yea</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">O horrible blaſphemy! None but Chriſt Jeſus is Truth it ſelf, and Truth it ſelf (ſaith this Prieſt) <hi>Apolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding.</note> 
               <hi>Truth it ſelf, and all Religion)</hi> is ſhaken, &amp; all that is ſhaken is <hi>of things that are [made]</hi> and that they are ſhaken, <hi>ſignifies the removing of thoſe things that are ſhaken, as of things that are</hi> [made] <hi>that thoſe things which cannot be ſhaken may remain,</hi> Heb. 12. 26, 27. But of theſe ſlaine <hi>heapes upon heapes,</hi> I finde no mention.</p>
            <p>I alſo weighed his [<note n="f" place="margin">Pag. 80. to pag 90.</note>] <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> his <hi>Coate,</hi> and <hi>Craft,</hi> and <hi>Generation,</hi> his [<note n="g" place="margin">Pag 80. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> pag. 34.</note>] <hi>Argument</hi> (in his Anſwer to his own objection) formed againſt the friends of truth as <hi>Knaves, Impoſtors,</hi> and <hi>Deceivers,</hi> and found it and them all too light, and proved them (turning his Argument on his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171621:6"/> own<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the heads of his generation) <hi>Knaves, Inter alliis,</hi> [they are his own words] <hi>Impoſtors, Deceivers,</hi> who ſay <hi>they are Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> and yet pretend not to the <hi>infallible</hi> ſpirit, which they had who were <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> who affirm <hi>that their neceſſary deductions from the Scriptures are as true and certain as the Scriptures;</hi> yea, <hi>that they are Scripture,</hi> and yet deny that they ſpeak by <hi>inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> (by which all <hi>Scripture was given)</hi> and as the <hi>holy men of God</hi> did, (who <hi>spake as they were moved of the Holy Ghoſt)</hi> or that they have <hi>infallibility,</hi> who declare that they <hi>deceive not the people in ſtretching beyond their line &amp; meaſure;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in ſtretching beyond their line and meaſure, in the line and meaſure of others, is the whole of their <hi>Trade</hi> of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination,</hi> who <hi>confeſs that they may he deceived, and may erre;</hi> and ſay that they <hi>do not lyingly and hypocritically pretend to an infallibility,</hi> and yet undertake to lead people the right way to ſalvation; the <hi>ground</hi> of whoſe <hi>Miniſtry</hi> is no other then <hi>according to practice to ſpeak from the Scriptures, [We pretend to no other, we preend not to infallibility,</hi> ſaith R. F.] in which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Satan,</hi> pag. 34.</note> are found the <hi>Devils</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> and the <hi>certainty</hi> of whoſe ſpeaking <hi>according to the ſpirit,</hi> is no other then their ſpeaking according to the Scriptures, <hi>whoſe dictates</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>they are,</hi> of which they are no more ſure then were the <hi>falſe prophets</hi> and <hi>devils</hi> aforeſaid, who ſpake the words of Scripture, and from the Scriptures, and according to the words of the Scriptures, and yet were reproved by Chriſt, and his Prophets, and Apoſtles, for ſo ſpeaking; for it is not the words that are ſaid, nor the actions that are done, but the nature in which they are ſaid and done, and from whence they proceed, that renders them good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted before the Lord; and there are but two natures, the Divine, and that which is in the tranſgreſſion; but two principles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the one of life, the other of death; as is the root of either, ſo is that which proceedeth from it; and he that miniſters can miniſter no other then that principle from which he miniſters, nor to any other then to that which is of the ſame principle, whether of death, or of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171621:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> life. And as for the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> they are for the <hi>Man of God,</hi> to be read, to be believed, to be fulfilled, to be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; they are the <hi>things of God,</hi> not to be made a trade of for ſo much a year, or to be talked, or ſpoken of from, or by the <hi>wiſdom of this world, no not in the words which mans wiſdom, but which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth—</hi>Here his lips are covered.</p>
            <p>Many horrible <hi>blaſphemies</hi> I charged him with, againſt the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Many notorious <hi>lyes, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and <hi>falſe accuſations;</hi> many <hi>filthy ſcoffs,</hi> and <hi>profane jeers,</hi> yea of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> many <hi>groſſe abſurdities, confuſions,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions,</hi> line againſt line, page againſt page, one part of his Book againſt the other, ſlaying and confounding one another, and he them, and they the end and drift of his work, of which he is ſilent.</p>
            <p>The <hi>juſtification</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and of <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> from his foul <hi>calumnies</hi> and <hi>aſperſions</hi> he hath not inform'd; nor hath he endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to quit himſelf of the inſtances of <hi>blood-thirſtineſs,</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by me on him and his Generation; nor of the aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz. The dog it is that bites, the Lamb doth never.</hi> Nor hath he ſaid a word of the great <hi>Tumult</hi> and <hi>Sedition</hi> of which I charged him to be the chief ſtirrer up, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal mover, nor of many things more; in all which ſhould I be particular, time would fail me, being the contents of the greateſt part of my anſwer; and with what jugling, lying, and ſophiſtication he hath replyed to the reſt, and how little to the purpoſe, I ſhall diſſect, and plainly make manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Now when as Reaſon would that of theſe things afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and the reſidue of my anſwer, he ſhould have cleared himſelf, or have been ſilent, (and ſo to have done, had been ſomewhat becoming the ſeriouſneſs of man) inſtead thereof, (as one forlorn and deſparate) h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> falls violently on my perſon, pouring forth at it the evil treaſures not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his own, but the venemous hearts of thoſe generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of whom, and their Treaſons, he appeares a Patron,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171621:7"/> and Advocate, who are (and he with them) become mine Enemies for having been inſtrumental (in the diſcharge of my Truſt) to the detecting and preventing their <hi>ſecret plots</hi> and <hi>bloody conſpiracies</hi> againſt the Common-wealth, and <hi>Treaſonable Adherencies</hi> to the chief and declared Enemies thereof, in the day of its general deſignment, and greateſt conflicts, not conſidering that amongſt wiſe men <hi>Recrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is alwayes accounted an indicament of a bad cauſe;</hi> and inſtead of making good a general charge, particularly to aſperſe, and perſonally to reflect, is a very foule ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh.</p>
            <p>And here (having gained the <hi>Cauſe)</hi> I might withdraw my Pen, and ſit down in ſilence till <hi>R. F.</hi> ſhall have quitted himſelf an honeſt man in print, and have taken off what is laid by me on him in that my Anſwer; it being reaſonable that he whoſe honeſty as to a Narrator, I have ſo highly impeach'd; whoſe Narrative in the material parts thereof, I have ſo fully anſwered; whoſe Miniſtry and Religion I have ſo manifeſtly overturned; whoſe ſhare in Chriſtianity himſelf hath ſo openly renounc't, ſhould ſo do before he gain credit unto what he hath now wrote, or receive from me thereunto a Reply.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as the level of his, and the poyſoned Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of the generation aforeſaid, (who ſhoot under his cover) is laid at my Reputation, as to matter of Fact; and for that his, and their entrance unto me is made thorough the Authority of <hi>Parliament,</hi> their High Court of juſtice, and the Cauſe of the Nation, for which all the blood hath been ſpilt in the late Wars, and in regard the Parliament (as is ſaid) have appointed to hear the Caſe of him whoſe Cauſe is the principal pleading of this Impoſtor at their next Seſſions. And becauſe after all the vomitings up of his venemous filth, he ſaith in his laſt page, <hi>And now from he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceforth let none of theſe Quakers trouble me, I have done with this gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ration; but if they will be troubling, let them know that I will not be troubled—And as for any further An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>plyes, Contendings or Debatings with them or him,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171621:7"/> 
               <hi>I declare this as my Goronis, my farewell to quakeriſm.</hi> (And ſo I may ſtay a long day e're I appear for clearing of my Innocency, and the juſtice of the State.) Therefore I ſhall (waving in this place all other particulars) immediately deſcend to engage him and his Confederates, in his and their Two great <hi>Battalions,</hi> the ſum and end of his Work, and the ſtrength of his miſchief, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>The caſe of</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>William</hi> L. <hi>Craven,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>in reference to</head>
               <item>My <hi>Selfe.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">I mention myſelf firſt, becauſe I am accuſed; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that I clear my own innocency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I appeare in the vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> 
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>State.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the firſt, <hi>viz. Cravens Caſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ralph Farmer</hi> in his <hi>Sathan Enthron'd,</hi> having vilely tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd me in the buſineſs of this man, I judg'd it neceſſary for the ſatisfaction of all ſuch as neither deſired nor deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the defamings of others, to declare my innocency therein, which I then did, and do again in theſe words, <hi>I do</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Throne,</hi> p. 102.</note> 
                  <hi>declare in the preſence of the Lord, before whom I fear, who ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the heart, and tryeth the reins, and bringeth every work to judgement, That I am clear and innocent therein; nor have I u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, nor do I know of any indirect proceeding in that whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of</hi> Craven <hi>and</hi> Fauconer. At this my declaration he raves exceedingly, and is greatly moved, ſingling it out in the front, and diſcharging againſt it the wrath and fury of the invenom'd body of that his Reply, well knowing that if that ſtand, he is caſt in the ground-work of his defamings of me, (on which he ſaith, pag. 117. <hi>his diſcourſe and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very is founded)</hi> as my Anſwer hath overturned the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his blaſphemings of the truth.</p>
               <p>But ſtand it doth before him who ſeeth all things <hi>(in the fear of whom I have ſpoken this twice)</hi> and I queſtion not but ſtand it will (notwithſtanding all this dirt) before the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and truly wiſe in heart, who ſhall read and ſeriouſly conſider what ſhall be ſaid in this matter.</p>
               <p>And here I ſhall not rehearſe, nor ſpeake to all he hath written, it deſerving neither, nor ſhall I trouble the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171621:8"/> with a voluminous diſcourſe (with whithe of neceſſity I muſt, ſhould J be particular in every thing) nor ſhal I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file my Pen with the repetition of all his unclean and unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury language in abuſe of me; but ſhall bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fly come to what he calls his Evidence, upon which he ſaith page 83. <q>Clear he is, That if any Jury in the world (of diſcreet, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, impartial, and underſtanding men) were to paſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, they would give in this verdict, That I do know of many indirect proceedings in the matter of the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> and <hi>Fauconer,</hi> and that J my ſelf hath uſed them, and that therefore I am not clear and innocent in this matter: Which I shall examine and ſcan, and then leave it to all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, impartial, ſober, diſcreet men, even to that of God in the conſcience, which is juſt to judge, Whether notwithſtanding all his Evidence, I am not clear and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; yea, whether his ſaid Evidence, <hi>viz.</hi> the pretended Paper ſaid by him to be ſigned by Major <hi>Fauconer</hi> on his Death-Bed, and the Book, entituled, <hi>The Lord Cravens Caſe, &amp;c.</hi> do not make me ſo to appeare.</q>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>For the pretended Paper, ſaid to be ſigned by</hi> Fauconer.</q>
               <p>Although the black character which himſelf hath drawn over the man as one moſt ſcandalous and perjur'd; and his producing the ſaid Paper in the behalf of his Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> to prove him ſuch, be material Arguments againſt himſelf for the invallidating the credit of any thing ſaid to be wrote, or ſigned, or ſpoken by <hi>Fauconer</hi> againſt me; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſaid pretended Paper, as it is ſet down by <hi>R. F.</hi> without date or witneſs, and with an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> foot, appears rather as a forged Libel, then a true Record, and ſo not to be taken notice of, eſpecially coming forth on the ſingle credit of him whom I have proved to be a falſifier of his own Records, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet upon ſuppoſition that the Paper is <hi>Fauconer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and that every word thereof as it is ſet down by R. <hi>F.</hi> without any variation, interpoſition, or omiſſion of word or ſyllable, was wrote and ſigned by him, and that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171621:8"/> it is all, and every word and ſyllable that was ſo wrote and ſigned, (which whether it be or not, I ſhall leave to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to judge, and thoſe who are concern'd to look after up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what by and by ſhall be offered to conſideration in that particular) I ſay, Upon ſuppoſition, as aforeſaid, I ſhall thereunto thus ſpeak.</p>
               <p>Firſt it ſaith, <hi>And here I dare not ſay that any man bribed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> p, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>me; no, none d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi> Whereby I am cleared from that falſe and ſlanderous imputation of corrupting <hi>Fauconer</hi> to ſwear falſly in the Caſe aforeſaid, which <hi>Cravens</hi> friends at the tryal of <hi>Fauconer</hi> at the Upper-bench, and the Author of the Pamphlet, entituled, <hi>A true and perfect Narrative, &amp;c.</hi> and R F. in this his Reply have ſo induſtriouſly ſought to fix upon me.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Words, <hi>I dare not ſay that any one bribed me; no, none did;</hi> do plainly intimate, That ſtrong temptations (to affirm the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſome did bribe <hi>Fauconer)</hi> were on him, who ever he were, that wrote it; but the dread or the righteous God, who pleadeth the cauſe of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, was ſuch upon him, that he ſaid, <hi>I dare not; no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> none did.</hi> Unto the witneſs of which God of truth, hadſt thou R. F. hearkened when (as thy ſelf confeſſes, pag. 18, 19) upon the firſt reading of the declaration of my innocency, (which thou calls my bold and daring appeal) it cauſed thee to make a ſtand, and ſeriouſly to obſerve it, and aſtoniſhed thee, and made thee to read it again, and to conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there might not be ſome equivocation in the language and expreſſion, [how was thy evil eye abroad R. F ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for iniquity?] which nor appearing to thee, thou then beganſt to think that poſſibly I might not be guilty, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an age, ſayeſt thou, wherein many things are charged upon many men very ſlightly and ungroundedly, and ſometimes very falſly, which is my caſe <hi>Ralph,</hi> in this matter, &amp; that by thy ſelf: I ſay, Hadſt thou ſtil hearkned thereunto, &amp; obeyed it, then thou hadſt done me right, as hath the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inſtead of wronging of me in ſo high &amp; wicked a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as thou haſt in this thy Reply, for which a ſtrict recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171621:9"/> thou haſt to make with him who is the Judge of all, before whom thou muſt ſhortly appear, and then thou ſhalt know what thou haſt done, and what it was that made thee ſtand, and ſeriouſly to conſider, and aſtoniſht thee, and put thee to reading again; and notwithſtanding thy evil eye which ſearched for equivocation in the language and expreſſion, to ſet it by, judged in my behalf the ſecond time, and cauſed thee to begin to think that poſſibly I might not be guilty, and further to expreſs thy ſelf as hath been ſaid, which is the truth, and which ſhall ſtand a witneſs againſt, and plead my cauſe with thee for ever; for I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent before the Lord in this thing, and his Witneſs it was that ſtopped thee in thy way this twice, and gave judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for me, and ſhall do it eternally againſt thee, the mouth of the Lord of Hoſts hath ſpoken it; though thou heeding, and being guided by that ſpirit which watched and ſearched for iniquity againſt the Witneſs, didſt ſuffer the evil o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to get over, and to hurry thee forth into very bitter and violent expreſſions of me, and didſt then, and haſt ſince (through the juſt judgement of God upon thee) trampled it under foot, and mayeſt do yet for a little ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, till the meaſure of thine iniquity be filled up; yet ſhall it revive again, and then ſhalt thou know that the Lord hath ſaid it, and that thou art the man, and that the things are true of thy ſelf which thou haſt uttered forth againſt, and upon occaſion of me in the following lines of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Now this Paper (which after much travel is procured and made uſe of as the foundation of this laſt attempt for the retrival of the ſaid eſtate, and the blemiſhing of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in order thereunto) acquitting me thus manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as hath been ſaid, what need I any further vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
               <p n="3">3. The particulars in which I am named in that Paper, are onely theſe:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>And here I utterly renounce, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> eſpecially a late Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet ſent to me by Capt. <hi>Biſhop;</hi> the cauſe of my writing that Pamphlet was, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:171621:9"/>
                  <p> And when I made a demur at the words <hi>Barbarous and inhumane Rebels,</hi> Capt. <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſaid, If you leave that out, you do nothing.</p>
                  <p>True, I had done great ſervices for them, but not by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; and Capt. <hi>Biſhop</hi> kept me low with ſmall pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, ſo that I was at his Bow.</p>
               </q>
               <p>To the firſt; J ſent him no ſuch Pamphlet as there is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated, nor put J him in any ſuch, either by my ſelf di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, or by under-actors upon the conſideration there mentioned, or any other.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond, J know not of, nor do J remember or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that any ſuch demur was made by him at any time, or that J returned any ſuch anſwer; nor that he ſcrupled his information; nor had J any ſuſpition that he was not clear in the certainty of any part thereof, [had it been ſo, J ſhould have ſtopt his depoſing thereof, though himſelf had offered it] but had he made ſuch a demur, and had J reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as is expreſſed, doth it therefore follow, or ſaith the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that J bade him ſwear it notwithſtanding, or left him otherwiſe then to his liberty, either to leave out theſe words, or to put them in, as he was ſatisfied in the truth of them, or the contrary, ſo to have done had been indirect dealing indeed, and ſuch an abominable wickedneſs as my ſoul ever abhorr'd: Beſides thoſe words pretended to be ſpoken in anſwer, are juſtifiable according to the common acceptation of that phraſe amongſt men.</p>
               <p>To the third, it is a further juſtification of me who by it am made to appear to have been ſo far from encouraging any ſuch thing as falſe information, or perjury in <hi>Fauconer,</hi> that though he had done great ſervices for the State, yet J kept him low with ſmall pittances, ſo that he was at my bow; What! to ſwear falſly? nay the contrary, as the reaſonable may judge.</p>
               <p>And here by the way the Reader may take notice of the confuſion of R. F. who one while ſeeks to prove that J cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted <hi>Fauconer</hi> with [great] ſums of money, expreſſing what they were, and by whom paid, pag. 90. Another by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171621:10"/> keeping him low with <hi>[ſmall]</hi> pittances, who affirms pag. 90. That though he were not bribed with money <hi>[before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand]</hi> yet it was promiſed him, and liberty too; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſaith, Why was it promiſed him? No doubt, That he might not flintch from his oath; ſo making it <hi>[after.]</hi> And a few lines following that demands, But I pray, Why was not the money <hi>[paid him which was promiſed?]</hi> and yet (in the next words) inſtances ſeveral ſums of money which (he ſaith) was <hi>[paid him by my direction;]</hi> and then ſaith, Why was not the money <hi>[promiſed him, now paid?]</hi> Thus as to <hi>money,</hi> and as to <hi>liberty,</hi> (having made a ſlanderous rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning my being the occaſion thereof, out of <hi>Newgate,</hi> (thereby endeavouring to prove the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the promiſe of liberty, as of money) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon me with a heap of notorious lyes therein) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs of both, <hi>viz. Money</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> he ſaith thus, <hi>But I ſay, Why was not his liberty procured him now? and the money paid him now?</hi> and immediately anſwers himſelf, <hi>Oh!</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the buſineſs was done, the Eſtate ſold, let him hang, let him ſtarve now; it may be the ſum promiſed him was too great, and they could not agree who ſhould pay it, the Eſtate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſold;</hi> (wickedly inſinuating a combination to make up his pack of ſcandalous falſhoods.) And thus like a ſwift Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madary, traverſing her ways, and as a Bear bereft of her Whelps, he raves up and down with <hi>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea</hi> and <hi>No;</hi> and <hi>It is ſo,</hi> and <hi>It is not ſo;</hi> doubling and redoubling the counter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and all to bring forth this lye and foul aſperſion on me, with which he ſorely travels, <hi>viz. That I bribed Fauco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners perjury;</hi> Which he being not able to compaſs, (his own ſayings in this point, as ſo many falſe Witneſſes not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among themſelves; but diſproving one another with Diametrical oppoſition) yet ſuch is his Wickedneſs, that he will have it ſo, notwithſtanding as aforeſaid, and that the pretended Paper (his <hi>Libels</hi> chief Engine raiſed up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my reputation) clears me (as doth my conſcience) of any ſuch thing in theſe full and expreſs Words, <hi>And here I dare not ſay that any one bribed me, no, none did;</hi> as hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171621:10"/> been rehearſed: This is Prieſt <hi>Farmer,</hi> and the villany of him who pretends himſelfe to be a Miniſter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
               <p>The Paper doth not ſay that <hi>Fauconers</hi> information, or thoſe Words, <hi>Barbarous and inhumane Rebels,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of it, aroſe from any one but himſelf; nor that any one knew that the information, or any particular thereof was falſe; or that any one, knowing it to be falſe, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed any means, or provoked him to ſwear it; but it ſaith, The Words, <hi>[viz.</hi> Barbarous and inhumane Rebels being once (not but once, as R. F. belyes it, pag. 89.) named by me, they were as quickly inſerted; Which (granting it to be ſo, though I know of no ſuch ſnatching) was no more then what ought to have been done, it freely proceeding from the Informant, and being of ſuch importance to the State, though R. F. keeps ſo great a-do in ſeveral pages, to wreſt it to the contrary: (So by the Paper) the fault, if any, lies on <hi>Faulconers</hi> part who gave the information, and who (it ſaith) falſly ſwore it, (as he ſince remembers, ſaith the Paper, not when he depoſed it) and upon no other; or if it be, it appears not on whom to fix it; for though the Words, [I was haſtily after a great ſickneſs provoked to it] ſeem to intimate the contrary; yet whether it was by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward temptation, or outward ſuggeſtion, (to either of which the term <hi>Provoke,</hi> is convertible) who can determine? or who it was that uſed ſuch provocation, ſeeing therein the Paper is ſilent? For my part I know of neither, nor of any ſuch haſt as the Paper mentions; or that the information, or any part of it was falſe; or that he doubted of the truth of any thing he depoſed; The information was wholly from himſelf, &amp; he was very free in giving it; and time there was enough [Dayes, and Weeks, and Months] for conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had he doubted in himſelf, between the firſt Diſcourſe, wherein <hi>Faulconer</hi> mentioned <hi>Cravens</hi> Name, and the beginning of his information, and the depoſing of what he had informed.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:171621:11"/>
[5. The <hi>Paper</hi> ſaith; <hi>So that</hi> I <hi>do here ſolemnly proteſt, that I did not then</hi> (when he made oath) <hi>abſolutely remember whether the very words Barbarous, and Inhumane Rebells were expunged;</hi> and premiſes theſe as the reaſons in the foregoing words <hi>viz. For after twenty Weeks ſickneſs</hi> (ſayth it) <hi>this was done, my body being low, and in much haſte, being much infeebled; and above three quarters of a year after I came over Sea;</hi> Which plainly clears his information as to thoſe words (and no other clauſe was inſiſted upon at the tryal as a perjury) from being a <hi>packt, feigned,</hi> or <hi>deſigned</hi> thing, and himſelfe from being guilty, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Corrupt, Wilfull,</hi> and <hi>Malitious perjury,</hi> (the verdict brought in by the jury againſt him:) And ſo what doth there remain as a ground of clamour? For on theſe two hinges, <hi>viz.</hi> That his information as to theſe words Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, and Inhumane Rebells was deſigned, feigned and packt, and that he wilfully and in malice, and being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted thereunto, ſware it doth turn all the late endeavours for the Retrivall of this Eſtate; and on theſe two Pillars is founded all the outcryes that hath been made of <hi>Fauconers</hi> Perjury, and of the injuſtice, and indirect dealing of the Parliament Counſell of State, their Committee for examinations, &amp;c. and of my ſelfe their ſecretary in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto, as the onely Game they had left to play, and the laſt ſtone they had to turn for that purpoſe; which nevertheleſſe (after all this great a do) is but as aforeſaid <q>by their own reckoning; for after twenty Weeks ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this was done, my bodie being low, and in much haſte, being much infeebled, and three quarters of a year af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I came over, ſo that I did not then abſolutelie remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, whether the word Barbarous and inhumane Rebells were expunged;</q> 
                  <hi>ſaith the paper:</hi> And that <hi>Fauconer</hi> drew the Petition, and that he put into it thoſe very words, <hi>Drury,</hi> and <hi>Briſca</hi> (the onely witneſſes againſt him at the tryal) confeſſed on their Oaths, though they ſaid they were afterwards expunged, <hi>ſo that as he ſolemnly proteſts,</hi> he did not well remember wheher thoſe words Barbarous
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171621:11"/> and Inhumane Rebels, which as I ſhewed you before, he motioned to have put into the Petition, and might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have ſome confuſed remembrance of them; <q> I ſay he could not well then in haſte (as he ſaith) remember whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were expunged, or no; ſaith <hi>R. Farmer,</hi> Page 89.</q> Here is the ſum of this whole matter, and the <hi>Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme</hi> on which it hangs, and the narrow compaſs into which it is drawn by the friends of <hi>Craven,</hi> and <hi>Fauconers</hi> enemies: And thus hath their evidence over-turned their cauſe, and their management thereof declared (againſt their wils) their jugling to Poſteritie.</p>
               <p>But whether the ſaid pretended paper, and the whole contents thereof be really <hi>Fauconers,</hi> and of his hand writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſigning, I ſhall offer a few particulars to men of underſtanding to conſider (and as I have ſaid) to thoſe who are concerned to look after.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I have by me a <hi>Declaration every line of his own hand writing and ſigning,</hi> to the contrary, which he ſent to me to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh in his vindication, without any fore-knowledge of mine, direction or preocupation either of the thing, or matter therein contained directly or indirectly, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>A Declaration of Major</hi> Ric. Fauconer, <hi>Priſoner in the Upper Bench, humbly tendred to all honourable perſons of truſt, and imployment, and to all other impartiall Readers.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>HAving endured a strict impriſonment theſe two years</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">His death pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the publiſhing of this Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                        <hi>and a quarter, being expoſed to all wants and extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, that poſſible a priſon can reduce a man unto; languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo in a deep</hi> Conſumption, <hi>contracted by my cruel ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; And for that I perceive the malice of my adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to be moſt inſatiable, by rendring me daily more &amp; more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious; thereby to invalidate my teſtimony concerning the</hi> Lord Craven: <hi>I have therefore after a ſtrict examination and ſcrutiny into my very ſoul, iſſued forth this enſuing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,</hi>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:171621:12"/> 
                        <hi>moſt humbly tendring it to the juſt cenſure of all honourable perſons of truſt and imployment, and to all other Impartial Readers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And firſt I declare of my ſelf, that as by Birth and Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I claim a parity with the better ſort of Gentlemen; ſo my affections were ſhewed moſt early to the Parliament, when the Fature Mountaynous troubles were but an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In the ſervice I continued conſtant in armes, even to the latter time of the late war; I alſo expended out of my Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony foure hundred Pounds, and upwards, in raiſing Horſe in</hi> Wales; <hi>as hath been and will be atteſted to by ſeverall Officers, under Major Generall</hi> Horton, <hi>of all which I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver received yet one Penny: After this I undertook my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment beyond Sea, there I run many hazzards, travell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many hundreds of miles, through</hi> France, Flanders, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and, Ierſey, <hi>&amp;c. to and again, &amp; peformed matters with all vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant care: On my return for</hi> England <hi>after a year and a halfes time, in the Packet Boat of</hi> Oſtend, <hi>the ſaid Boat was robbed, and ſome ſeventeen or eighteen Paſſengers car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed Priſoners, and my ſelfe onely and the Boatmen free; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this I obſerved the hand of Providence then, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved me to come ſafe to</hi> London, <hi>where I rendred an ample account all of the whole Treaty at</hi> Breda, <hi>and all the tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with divers matters of importance; As my ſervices were many, ſo I ſhall inſtance but one to avoid prolexity, and by that the whole body of the other may be judged;</hi> Expede Herculem.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>At</hi> Breda, <hi>ſeverall commiſſions were granted by the Scotch King, for the raiſeing of horſe and foot in divers parts of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, <hi>by thoſe numerous inſurrections to have gained a Body of an Army, whereby to have diverted the</hi> Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, <hi>and the Army, from hindering the Scotch in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign for England; this was carried with much ſecreſie by the principall Agents there, the chiefeſt, and moſt deſperate of thoſe inſurrections as well as the reſt; notwithſtanding the great ſecreſie, I gave a particular account of four</hi>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:171621:12"/> 
                        <hi>Months before it hapned; nay of the Colonell who was chief Agent, and taken an actor with ſeverall others: By this timely hint the Parliament had time enough to prevent their enemies; which they did, and by cruſhing them, all the intended inſurrections in the</hi> Weſt, <hi>and</hi> Wales, <hi>they vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: The Parliament and councill of State did ſolemnize a day of thanksgiving at</hi> Margrets <hi>in</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and orderd a day to be obſerved thorough the whole Nation for that great deliverance, of which inſtrumentally under God I was the principal Author; and Judge</hi> Jermine <hi>was pleaſed to tell Mr.</hi> Maynard, <hi>who was moſt bitter againſt me, that without that ſervice of mine, and ſome others, neither he had ſet there, nor Mr.</hi> Maynard <hi>pleaded there: I wonder</hi> Drury <hi>and</hi> Briſco, <hi>did not acquain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> State with the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded dangers, they both knew it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Breda: <hi>No, they ſtayed to ſee the laſt man born of all the Royal Games; and then came into</hi> England <hi>after they could act no more miſchiefe, as good Common Wealths men.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And now a word or two of them, the chief evidence againſt me, I have in part related what I have been, what I have acted, and what J am, and let the indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent man Ballance us; <hi>Drury</hi> was alwayes a Papiſt in armes againſt the Parliament; ſo irreconcileable an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, that after all endeavors at home, he Petitioned the then Scotch King, (as himſelf confeſſed at the Upper Bench Court) to be enabled to ſerve him, as he had done his royal father: one who went from <hi>Bredato Antwerpeto</hi> place his ſonn there with the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> this he cannot deny &amp; J am ſure divers can teſtifie it: For <hi>Briſco,</hi> there was enough declared on Oath concerning him <hi>viz.</hi> that he betrayed and ſold his Countreymen for twelve ſtivers a man, he was alwayes an invetterate enemy againſt the State, and formerly belonged to the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Regiment; J will ſpare to touch at their perſonal vices, although ſome of them have falſely blaſted me, and rendred me odious, and notorious of which J ſhall ſpeake anon. And now J de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of all honeſt men to judge, whether my evidence may
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171621:13"/> not ſtand in Competition with theirs; <hi>Drury</hi> confirmes that J drew the Petition, alſo, which was preſented at <hi>Breda,</hi> and ſure J have then beſt reaſon to remember the contents of it; notwithſtanding a Copy which he ſaid he preſerved in his Sonns book, yet that was but a Copy; not the mayn originall Petition, nor can <hi>Drury</hi> upon his Oath deny, but that himſelf related to me and others, that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> told him, it would not be ſafe for him to deliver the Petition; but he would ſpeake to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> this he cannot deny on Oath, unleſs by a mental reſervation, he can diſpence with any Oath: If this man who hath forfeited his life may ſtand in competition with me; nay overthrow my evidence, who ſo long ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured my life, and who have been under God, a means of ſo great deliverance to the Army and Nation; then I may ſafely cry aloud, <hi>Terras Aſtraea reliquet;</hi> indeed a large and a ſtrange Verdict was obtained againſt me on their evidence; <hi>viz.</hi> Corrupt, Willful and Malitious Perjury; but I would be informed where either of the three were, or on what evidence the jury ſhould ground it, to bring in corruption, Malice &amp; Wilfulneſs; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> as for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption Ideclare before God, &amp; to the whole world, that I never was inticed animated, or procured, to put in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation given by me at white H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll, touching the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> by any perſon or perſons whatſoever nor did Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver receive one penny of money, or any monies or reward to do it, or for doing it: My long &amp; extream povertie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in a periſhing condition may eaſilie confirme it. For Malice J am ſure the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> perſon was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unknown to me, untill the Treaty at <hi>Breda;</hi> &amp; for Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, it was upon oath atteſted by an Honourable &amp; an honeſt Patriot, that it was firſt accidentally delivered in diſcourſe; of which when J was called before a publique authority, J thought in my conſcience, and do ſtill think, J was obliged to declare the truth, and in this J will live and dye.</p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:171621:13"/>
                     <p> Nor can I omit the ſubtile malice of my proſecutors, who being back'd at home &amp; abroad with potent Friends and large Purſes, compaſſed Sea and Land to gain their Proſelytes (whileſt I was detained moſt ſtrictly in priſon) by them to blaſt me in my Repute, ſo to make vvay to their Verdict, <hi>Knight,</hi> the firſt of thoſe Proſelytes, was condemn'd to be hang'd at <hi>Tiburn,</hi> and was carryed in the Cart as far as the Bars in <hi>Holborne:</hi> The reſt were Catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poles, and Catchpoles-followers; onely Mr. <hi>Worllage</hi> an Attorney, who could not charge me with any particulars: and one <hi>Jaques, alias Jackson,</hi> the ſon of a Bailiff, one who by the ruine of many yong men and others, from a poor Ale-houſe, came to be an Inne-Keeper. Theſe were their good ſubſtantial Evidence, as they tearm them; nay, this <hi>Jackson</hi> was proſecuted by Mr. <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rllage</hi> for cheating a Neighbor of his with falſe Dice, of a great ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. This <hi>Jackson</hi> was perjured in a deep manner; and if he can produce any one to atteſt what he falſly ſwore, <hi>viz. That I on my knees drank a health to the Devil at noon-day in the Market-Town of Peters-field ſome ſix years ſince,</hi> as he falſly and wickedly ſwore, I will, as J ſhould deſerve, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the moſt ignominious death: Jt is ſtrange that at Noon-day, on a Market-day, and in the Market-place, none ſhould ſee or hear this; No ſurely, nor perjured <hi>Jackson</hi> neither; and J beſeech God in his due time to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt this exemplarily on one of us, either by his mercy or juſtice.</p>
                     <p>And that the World may moſt apparently behold the machivilian projects, and peſtilent divices of my adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries; I do here declare, that after that falſe verdict obtained againſt me, ſeverall Agents, and ſome of them <note place="margin">Note.</note> perſons of good quality oft times were with me, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited me to diſcover &amp; acknowledge what I was not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, offering me from my chiefe adverſaries indempni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Liberty, &amp;c. And if any ſhall ſay, this is but my bare aſſertion, and that I will ſay any thing to help my ſelfe in this ſad and deſperate condition; to them I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171621:14"/> and to my adverſaries, that I defie them in this, and that I have their Letters under their hands kept ſafe, to this hour; wherein I am offered indemnitie, Liberty, &amp;c. So that I would but comply in their devices, with them to the ruine of others, and ſhipwrack of my ſoul and conſcience: Theſe <note n="*" place="margin">Theſe Letters I have by me.</note> Letters I ſay I have, and it was a long time on treaty, and if I produce not theſe let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters before any authority, than let me be hanged, and ſpare not: Surely theſe men have dealt with me, as ſome Witch-finders do, as I have heard, who have put poor innocent old Women to ſo great torture, that they have been forced to confeſs themſelves Witches, though nothing ſo, chuſing a preſent death rather then their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued torments; but let their crueltie be as rageing as Hell, and Devill himſelf, as I am expoſed to all wants, and deſerted by all, I ſhall yet rather chuſe to walk in the direct line of my conſcience, than divide from the truth: To conclude, as all and each perticular in this my declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is truth, ſo I once more declare before God, and to all men, that no manner of perſon or perſons whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <note place="margin">Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e,</note> did in the leaſt, intice, perſwade, move, or procure me to give in the information touching the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> at <hi>White Hall,</hi> but as I have declared, I thought my ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to declare the verity before a publique authority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which authority I was called after I had acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally diſcovered it in diſcourſe to a perſon of quality, and truſt.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Rich. Fauconer.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p n="2">2. Hee ſuffered a very ſharp and cruel impriſonment in <hi>Newgate,</hi> and the Upper Bench Priſons, under ſuch deep neceſſitie of apparell, bedding and other Proviſions, that he was even <hi>eat with Vermin, and waſted with an incuraeble Cough, and Conſumption,</hi> (as from himſelfe by many ſad and lamentable Letters, expreſſing how his <hi>Doggs and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, stood warmer and cleaner in the dayes of his proſperity,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:171621:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> and by others I have been informed (that he dyed; dure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which time of his ſaid ſad impriſonment, both before and after his Tryal, he was treated, tempted, and ſought to be corrupted, <hi>die in diem</hi> from day to day for many weeks together, not onely with Threatning, and Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying expreſſions that he <hi>ſhould be ſeverely proſecuted, his Cheeks Branded, his Noſe ſlit, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch like,</hi> but with large offers of Money, Liberty, Indemnity, and the ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all, to ſome ſuch thing, of himſelf and me, as is the intent and drift of the recitall, and uſe made of this Paper: now produced after his death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſaid by <hi>Ralph Farmer</hi> to be his, which (when living) he withſtood, and choſe rather thus by lingering crueltie to waſt into death, than by yeilding thereunto [and ſo to make himſelfe and others guilty, who are innocent] to live, though in the poſſeſſion of the largely promiſed Indemnitie, Money, and Libertie.</p>
               <p>Now of this Tampering to corrupt him, I was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie informed at <hi>White Hall,</hi> from time to time as it was tranſacting, but I have the Papers by me readie to make i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appear, yea the original Letters (ſubſcribed and wrote all with the ſame hand) of the copies of which, and the Negotiations of that perſon and his outward qualitie; he thus expreſſes;</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>Now Sir, I have ſent you a Copy of two Letters, of which I have the originalls by me, whereby you may perceive how they have been at me; their ſpleen being at Coll. <hi>Joyce,</hi> your ſelf, and others, &amp;c. I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born to affixe his name, in regard he is a Gentleman of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: Aſſoone as it is known that I have imparted it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſhall be ſurely murthered (which I am confident is far from your deſire.) Now I am deeply engaged to ſecreſie, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould the Gentleman be ſummoned, and I remain here where he hath a Brother Priſoner; I ſay again I ſhould be ſurely and out of hand murthered: This Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man came in all haſte to me, aſſoon as he underſtood the Book mentioned their large offers to me before, and ſince my tryal (now, this Gentleman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                           <desc>•••••</desc>
                        </gap>ed with me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171621:15"/> and ſince my tryal) and ſaid it could not poſſibly be but I had revealed it to you, but I proteſted you knew not his name, which I am ſure you do not, although I wrote to you of the matter in generall, but I told him that indeed, one went to you, and told you of ſome large proffers were made me, which in part pacified him; J have the originall Letters ſubſcribed with his hand, and he is a Gentleman of worth and good deſcent; And in the Poſtſcript he ſaith, as J ſhall anſwer it at the Dreadful day of Judgement, to my knowledge J have not written one falſe matter or circumſtance in this Letter.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Rich. Fauconer.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Beſides the aforeſaid, J have (among the reſt) a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of another, (whoſe name I ſhall forbear to mention) who (he ſayes) is a Gentleman of quality, and an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and intimate acquaintance of his, and who came to him, and tampered with him in the ſame matter, and told him, that he could tel how to put a brace of hundred <note place="margin">He o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ten ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsed himſelf that he was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſome Hundreds a year if he would ſay, he was Corrupted.</note> pounds into his Pocket concerning the <hi>Lord Craven.</hi> And that a Parliament man aſſured him (his ſaid friend) that if he would but ſubſcribe who inticed him to it, that the Lord CRAVEN would recover his Eſtate, and how they were conſpireing to have all his creditors to arreſt him, &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with much more, which J ſhall forbear further to repeat: The poor man through extremity of miſery (though <hi>Chiefe Juſtice Rolls,</hi> and the Judges of the Upper Bench, ſaw cauſe to arreſt Judgement; which arreſt of Judgement they never tooke off) is languiſhed and dead, his blood will lye ſomewhere and be required; for my part J am cleare.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thoſe Paſſages, [J here proteſt before the Almighty God, that J never nudertooke any imployment, nor never any one mentioned it to me, but J went over in a poor deſperate condition, ſupported by others;] And [true, J had done great ſervices for them, but not by imployment] Renders the ſaid Paper either very unlikely to be <hi>Fauco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:171621:15"/> or (if R. F. and his fellowes will have it to be his yet) that it is not truth, and ſo the Paper is not to be beleived upon the account of the confeſſion of a dyeing man; for that he was imployed beyond the Seas to diſcover the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the enemy againſt the Common Wealth, Lievt. Coll. <hi>Joyce</hi> depoſed in Court, at the tryall, as being diſcourſed with by him thereabouts before he went over; and Lievt. Coll. <hi>Joyce</hi> it was that brought him to me (after he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) to give an account of the diſcoverie he had made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas of their conſpiracies; and himſelf hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it under his hand in his Declaration aforeſaid, &amp; that he was imployed afterwards, others can teſtifie; againſt which ſo known a truth to himſelfe and others and by him ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeribed, for <hi>Fauconer</hi> to proteſt &amp; affirme as aforeſaid is moſt improbable, and hardly to be ſuppoſed, as the matter of the ſaid Proteſtation, and aſſertion appears to be moſt notoriouſly falſe; which being ſo in theſe particulars, ſo ſolemnly in words proteſted and affirmed; what credit is to be given to the reſt of the ſaid Paper, as of the words of a dyeing man pretended to be delivered under the ſence (as it ſaith) of a touched conſcience, and from a ſoul woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully perplexed; Upon the bare reputation of which; <hi>(viz.)</hi> as the words of a dying man ſo ſenſibly expreſt; this Paper for the ends aforeſaid is dropt into the world as truth to be beleived, but is thus proved a lye and blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>And thus much concerning this pretended Paper <hi>(Ra. Farmers</hi> main foundation of what he calls his evidence, and indeed, upon the matter, the ſum of it) and to what I ſeem therein to be concerned.</p>
               <p>For the other particulars which he endeavors to fix upon me, as indirect dealing from certain paſſages out of the Book, intitled the <hi>Lord Craven caſe:</hi> &amp;c. pick't, parceld, and mangled by him, and then ſet down as his other ground of (what he calls) his evidence for that purpoſe: I need no clearer vindication than that very Book, wherein is not onely related, ſtated at large, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171621:16"/> argued that whole buſineſſe of <hi>Craven</hi> and <hi>Fauconer;</hi> but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, &amp; thoſe very things which he layes to my charge an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered in a ſhort examination of a certain Pamphlet intitled, (A true &amp; perfect Narrative of the ſeverall proceedings in the caſe concerning the Lord <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aven,</hi> &amp;c. The ſubſtantialitie and truth whereof he hath not (by any thing that he hath ſaid) infirme, nor can he refell; yea thoſe very paſſages as related by him, conſidered abſtractively from the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the pretended paper, which by horrible wreſting he hath ſought to make ſpeak, what they ſay not, and then hath joyned them to thoſe paſſages to force them (if he could) to pronounce the ſame, (which I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cut off and anſwered) cleare me ſufficiently; therefore I ſhall not (being deſirous to eaſe the Reader) rehearſe what he hath ſaid therein, nor further anſwer to it as I might, though ſo to do would tend much to the infamy of him, and my advantage; but ſhall refer the unprejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Reader to the ſaid Book, &amp; the Pamphlet examined as aforeſaid, and that part of R F<hi>'s</hi> reply, wherein are thoſe paſſages, &amp; upon ſerious conſideration of the one &amp; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with this my defence, let him judge, whether Ineed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire amore fair &amp; fuller vindication? And whether any man (beſides R. F. and ſuch as are led by his ſpirit) pretending to ingenuity or honeſty, would not have bluſhed ſo to have produced &amp; miſuſed them as he hath done? whoſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered bowels ſo plainly work to convert againſt me, what is my juſtification; and whoſe black malitious ſpirit ſo apparantly runs through the body and members of what he hath written as the very ſource and contagion thereof, that I need not give it any further demonſtration; And indeed were it otherwiſe, yet it is ſo circularly interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with mingle mangles, and wrapt up with ſuch interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory uncertainties and Ironicall reflections, that there is nothing ſo poſitive as might deſerve a rationall reply; and the ground work or foundation falling, or rather ſhakeing, of what he hath ſought to build thereupon, what he hath endeavored ſo to raiſe muſt needs come to the ground; True it is, I readily lent him (at his deſire) the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171621:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Book</hi> aforeſaid partly to try what he would do therewith, &amp; partly to leave him without excuſe although I then expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome ſuch wretched miſ-uſe thereof as he hath made, &amp; poyſonous extraction which the Book it ſelf corrects, to the recording of his ſhame and diſingenuitie for ever.</p>
               <p>And now having (or rather what he hath produced as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence againſt me) cleared my innocencie from his groſs and ſlanderous imputations, I ſhall proceed to ſpeake a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more particularly of this matter, the clamor whereof hath made ſuch a ring in this Nation.</p>
               <p>To what hath been already ſaid, I do further declare, that as I have uſed no indirect dealing, ſo it hath not been in my heart, or deſire at any time to do this man wrong, much leſſe to deſigne the ruine of his Eſtate, that J might have part, as is moſt falſely ſuggeſted; my ſoul even abhorr'd, and my hands have alwayes been kept clear from any ſuch wickedneſs, (as my whole courſe in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique affairs &amp; many families in this Nation whom J freely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured (as J ſaw juſt cauſe) to keep from ruine, and was inſtrumentall to preſerve, (can witneſs:) But being intruſted by the State J was faithfull thereunto, that the Common-Wealth might receive no detriment, and did (in the diſcharge thereof) communicate what came to my knowledge of him (as of others) to thoſe in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity whom it did concern, who conſidered and did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as they ſaw appertained to juſtice; And that I neither deſired nor deſigned to do him wrong, but the contrary, I ſhall give one plaine (I may ſay undeniable) Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, of which I leave the reaſonable to judge, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Drury</hi> and <hi>Briſco</hi> (the two onely Witneſſes againſt <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner</hi> as to perjury) being in cuſtody by vertue of the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> of <hi>State's</hi> Warrant, as Traytors, and under my Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; J had then an opportunity (had J deſired or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned any ſuch thing as R<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> F. layes to my charge, or had been ſuch a man as he repreſents me) to have ſhut the door againſt this laſt attempt, <hi>(viz.</hi> the conviction of <hi>Fauconer)</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:171621:17"/> for the retriving of this Eſtate, and conſequently to have prevented all that wrong and abuſe which (in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto) hath been ſince done me (bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h in print and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) by his Agents and Advocates. For theſe two having been alwayes Enemies to the <hi>Common-we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lth,</hi> and in arms againſt it; the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a Collonel [a Papiſt] the other a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; and having been at <hi>Breda</hi> in the time of the Treaty there, and the concluſion thereof between the Scotch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners and their King, where (and in thoſe parts) they waited for new Employment (under him) againſt the State, <hi>till they were ready to periſh,</hi> and then petitioned him <hi>to take into his Princely conſideration their extremities who had been alwayes ready to proſtrate their lives in his Majeſties moſt royal Fathers ſervice, and were no leſs willing and ready to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the ſame in what he ſhould command, and that ſome courſe might be taken for their preſent ſubſiſtance, that their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture endeavors might not be buryed in that unavoidable calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which their known loyalty had reduced them unto,</hi> (as the <hi>Petition</hi> hath it, which <hi>Drury</hi> upon examination tendered to me as the original draught of the <hi>Petition</hi> preſented by themſelves and other Officers, to the ſaid King for the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of their deſires) wherein they entreated the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> aſſiſtance. And <hi>Drury</hi> appearing to me (as did <hi>Briſco)</hi> by his pleading on <hi>Cravens</hi> behalf before <hi>I</hi> asked him one queſtion, or ſignified the reaſon of his apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and by his continual interjecting his Plea to the ſame purpoſe throughout his examination, to have come over from beyond the ſeas upon ſome ſuch Errand, as they were afterwards made uſe of: And they both having given me in their Examinations under their hands, an account of their bearing arms againſt the Common-Wealth from firſt to laſt, and of their being at <hi>Breda,</hi> and doing as aforeſaid, <hi>I</hi> might either have recommitted them to priſon, or in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon detained them, or have procured them to be tryed for their lives, and executed as Traytors (they being deſperate Enemies to the <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> and without the Act of Pardon, and coming over without the allowance of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171621:17"/> 
                  <hi>State,</hi> and their own Examinations, as well as others, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing againſt them) or have taken from <hi>Drury</hi> the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal draught of the ſaid <hi>Petition,</hi> wrote (as was ſaid) with <hi>Fauconers</hi> hand; and ſo there had been neither matter on which to raiſe, or Witneſſes whereby to effect what hath been done againſt <hi>Fauconer:</hi> But contrary hereunto, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued their liberty upon paroll, and took not from <hi>Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the ſaid draught of the ſaid <hi>Petition;</hi> and when I was ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome why I did ſo, as foreſeeing and being ſenſible of the uſe that would be (and which hath ſince been) made of it againſt the <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> and expreſſing ſomewhat to that purpoſe; I replyed to this effect, That J did ſo in regard there were mutterings abroad, as if the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> had received wrong, and now that there were ſome which could teſtifie in his behalf, the <hi>Council</hi> had laid their power upon them. And I added, That whatever were the iſſue, yet this I had done in uprightneſs, and that the <hi>Common-Wealth</hi> might not ſuſtain the leaſt blemiſh upon their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. And this is the naked truth as it was in my heart; for it was always my deſire, and I often expreſt it, That the <hi>Common-Wealth</hi> might not have a Tittle of any mans but what was right; and the ſame I purſued as I ſaw juſt cauſe, and had opportunity and power, and bore my Teſtimony againſt ſuch as endeavoured the contrary.</p>
               <p>Now whereas it may be ſaid, <hi>How do theſe things agree with the remanding</hi> Drury <hi>to the cuſtody of the Serjeant at Arms, and detaining of him there till the end of that Seſſions, wherein the Indictment was found againſt</hi> Fauconer; <hi>ſo that a Tryal could not be had before his conviction, and before the next Seſſions the vote paſſed for ſale of his Eſtate? And with the not reporting of</hi> Drury <hi>and</hi> Briſco's <hi>Examinations aforeſaid, which tended to the vindication of the Lord</hi> Craven; <hi>when as thoſe that made againſt him were reported?</hi> And <hi>with my purchaſing a conſiderable part of his Eſtate?</hi> (all which <hi>R. F.</hi> hath laid to my charge as <hi>indirect dealing,</hi> (and therein keeps a great a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>do) from the <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> entituled, <hi>A true and perfect Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:171621:18"/>
               <p> I anſwer, Although that Pamphlet; with all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars therein, and the reſidue of the contents thereof, are at large argued and anſwered in the aforeſaid Book, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Lord Cravens Caſe,</hi> which, as I have ſaid, I lent <hi>R. F.</hi> at his deſire, that of the truth of things in behalf of the Commonwealth, he might not be ignorant, and unto which (becauſe not refell'd or infirm'd by <hi>R. F.)</hi> J have already, to avoid prolixity, referr'd the Reader for ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; yet that J may not ſeem to avoid ſpeaking becauſe unable to anſwer; nor leave the Reader for the clearing of theſe things, at ſuch a diſtance as the peruſual of thoſe books which he may not have by him; J ſhall in ſhort Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To the firſt, <hi>Drury</hi> was not remanded into ſafe cuſtody by me for any ſuch intent or purpoſe in the leaſt, as to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct proceedings that Seſſions, nor was it ſo much as in my thoughts; but becauſe <hi>Drury</hi> being a priſoner to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil for Treaſon, which he &amp; his fellow <hi>Briſco</hi> had confeſſed, &amp; under examination, did ſuffer himſelf to be treated, ſworn, and examined in a Caſe wherein the Common-Wealth was concern'd, without firſt acquainting the Council or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, or me (who had let him have his liberty upon pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rol) therewith, which he ought to have done; or declaring unto them (who ſo treated, ſwore, &amp; examined him,) that he was in ſuch a condition, by which his behaviour he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared not to be in that indifferency and uprightneſs as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Witneſs, but in combination againſt the <hi>State,</hi> whoſe Priſoner he was: Not that the offence was becauſe he was examined on his Lords behalf (had that been the thing in deſign to hinder, it could, as hath been ſaid, eaſily have been prevented either by keeping him and <hi>Briſco</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, or taking away the draught of their petition, or having them both tryed:) Nor that J apprehended that his Teſtimony could acquit his Lord of the guilt, for which the Parliament adjudged his Eſtate to be confiſcated; his very examination being a further proof of his Lords delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not an acquittal, as anon vvill appear. Nor that proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171621:18"/> ſhould not have been had againſt <hi>Fauconer</hi> in a legal way, (had it been ſo, he would have been detained longer then four dayes, and his Lords Friends conſtrained to have paſt thorough the bars and locks of the Authority of the Council (which was by Act of Parliament) thereunto) but for the Reaſons aforeſaid. Nor had <hi>Drury</hi> been at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, could there [reaſonable] have been expected a Tryal that Seſſions, though the <hi>Narrator</hi> aforeſaid, on whoſe bottom, or rather falſhood, R. <hi>F.</hi> hath raiſed this ſlander upon me, hath alledged, That <hi>Fauconer might have been try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, had not Drury been reſtrained by me,</hi> and layes it before the Reader, as if his not being tryed that Seſſions, was the ground wherefore the paſſing of the Bill engroſt, was not prevented: <hi>And before the next Seſſions,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Bill of ſale of the Lord Craven's Eſtate to be ſold, did paſs;</hi> For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>Fauconer</hi> (who muſt have pleaded to the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ere a Tryal could have been) ſummoned to appear; nor was he in cuſtody; nor was there a certainty whether he might be found in that ſhort ſpace of time wherein <hi>Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> was detained<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which was but four dayes; or had he been found, ſummon'd, or attach't, could it be expected that (in a caſe of ſuch concernment to himſelf and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth) he ſhould have Witneſſes, in ſo ſhort a time, ready, the matter of Fact being done beyond the ſeas ſome years before, where none but Enemies to the State were preſent, (who muſt be, if any, his Compurgators) and the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment's</hi> adjudging of the Caſe, having put by the expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any ſuch Tryal; or that the chief Juſtice <hi>Rolls</hi> would have bound him up peremptorily to have pleaded within that time, and ſo conſequently have conſtrained him to impoſſibilities, he having ſo rational and juſt ground of Plea for a longer: Nor (had all theſe things concurr'd) could it have been tryed that Seſſions, in regard the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was wrong laid; or if it had been tryed, could it have done otherwiſe then miſcarry? for that the original depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on which the Indictment was grounded and recited in <hi>hac Verba,</hi> could not be found, as is more at large argued in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171621:19"/> 
                  <hi>Cravens</hi> Caſe aforeſaid, pag. 31, 32, 33, 34. which R. F. (ſuch is his fallacious manner of dealing where he cannot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer) calls a <hi>company of blind ſuppoſals, and childiſh arguings;</hi> and bids me <hi>print it,</hi> and ſaith <hi>hee'l be my bondman if it any way help me, nay, if it doth not further diſcover my folly,</hi> and that <hi>he would have wrote it, but that,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>it is as long as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent;</hi> and then ſaith, <hi>This is enough.</hi> [Prieſt-like indeed.] But whether his ſaying ſo, doth convict the thing, or ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me, or him as deſerving that which he caſts on me, and whether he be not my <hi>bondman,</hi> let men of underſtanding upon peruſing theſe paſſages, and what is here aſſerted, judge.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>ſecond,</hi> I neither tranſmitted, nor reported any of the informations in this affair to the Parliament, nor was I ſo to do, but to the Committee of the Council of State for examinations and diſcoveries, who reported them to the Council of State, and the Council to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; unto which Committee I communicated the ſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations of <hi>Drury</hi> and <hi>Briſco,</hi> as I had done the others; but neither from them, nor the Council, received I any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to tranſmit them, or not, and ſo had nothing further lying upon me as my duty, but to keep them ſafe with the reſt of the things of that nature with which I was entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; nor do J know of any reaſon wherefore the Council reported them not; perhaps it was (and it is very likely the reaſon) becauſe the Parliament took not the informations on which they grounded their firſt vote of confiſcation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into conſideration; but notwithſtanding the often and long debates afterwards, during the ſpace of full ſeventeen Months, and what was offer'd, urg'd, and earneſtly ſought to be inforc't upon his behalf, ſtill ſaw cauſe to adher unto what they had at firſt voted; and ſo the Council might judge the reporting of theſe needleſs, eſpecially being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken above a year after their firſt information, as their dates make manifeſt.</p>
               <p>But as for concealing theſe Examinations becauſe they cleared his ſaid Lord, which the <hi>Narrator</hi> aforeſaid, pag. 44.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171621:19"/> and R F. pag 96, 97<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 98, 99, 100. and to know the reaſon of me wherefore the Council of State reported them not; <hi>Cravens Council</hi> ſo much inſiſted upon in proſecution of this queſtion, for that purpoſe in behalf of his Lord, at the Committee of Parliament fitting in the <hi>Star-Chamber No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.</hi> 23. 1654. to whom his Petition was refer'd as <hi>unjuſt and indirect dealing, and done in deſign to ruin his Eſtate,</hi> and of which ſo much clamor is made. J ſay, Jt's an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and falſe calumny; for, as J have ſaid, J concealed them not, but communicated them, as J did the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations; nor have J known nor perceived any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in the Council or their Committees in letting them lye unreported, or any thing in them but <hi>integrity</hi> and <hi>uprightneſs</hi> in this whole buſineſs, as J then declared to the Committee of Parliament aforeſaid, and am now made free to do the <hi>Council</hi> and their <hi>Committee</hi> this right in the face of all men; and that this is ſo, their permitting <hi>Drury</hi> and <hi>Briſco</hi> to enjoy their liberties upon what J ſaid to ſome of them as aforeſaid and <hi>Drury</hi> to keep the pretended o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal draught of the Petition, and not reſtraining their liberties afterwards, nor trying them, nor at all hindering the courſe taken for the conviction of <hi>Fauconer;</hi> nor inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing with their, or the Authority of Parliament, then ſitting: Theſe proceedings though of ſo bold and high a nature (as the like hath not been heard of) and tending in the very foundation of them (as is manifeſt by the uſe ſince made of it) to the ſcandalizing of their proceedings, and arraignment of their juſtice, is a plain demonſtration. Had J known to the contrary, <hi>I</hi> ſhould not have kept ſilence, but have born my Teſtimony againſt it, as having received mercy not to have ſerved (knowing it to be ſo) the baſe ends, or unjuſt commands of any in Authority, or other perſon upon any conſideration whatſoever.</p>
               <p>To conclude this particular, let the impartial underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding men in the Laws (who are Friends to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth) read and weigh the Examinations of <hi>Drury</hi> and Briſco, hereunto annexed, and judge whether inſtead of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171621:20"/> clearing their Lord from the guilt of Delinquency, <hi>viz. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herency to the Enemy of this Commonwealth,</hi> (the ground on w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Parliament voted the Confiſcation of his Eſtate, of which more by and by) they do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prove it ſtrongly upon him? And whether they are not ſufficient enough in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to bottom a ſequeſtration upon, (by the Law) were there no other Teſtimony? Finally, If ſo be the ſaid Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of thoſe two men (their choice Witneſſes for the diſproving of <hi>Fauconers</hi> Teſtimony, the grand Wheel on which hath turned all the late tranſactions in <hi>Cravens</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half) do render him guilty, (as upon peruſal and weighing, let it be judged whether it doth not ſo appear) what need there any more to be ſaid for the clearing of the Council, the Committee, and my ſelf from the foul calumnies and falſe ſuggeſtions, as aforeſaid, of concealing the ſaid Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations which they ſay (and thereupon make ſuch a noiſe) tended to his juſtification?</p>
               <p n="3">3. To the laſt, I did contract for part of his Eſtate, and why might I not as well as another, being ſold by Act of Parliament upon their Judgement of Delinquency? But I withdrew, and went not thorough with my Contract be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I foreſaw what uſe (as hath been ſince diſcovered) would be made thereof, <hi>viz. The rendring of me a party,</hi> and ſo to cut off my Teſtimony in the behalf of the Common-Wealth, (which Teſtimony of mine is their great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and a principal cauſe of the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inging up of all this, and the reſt of the dirt in this <hi>Libel,</hi> and other-where up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me) though ſuch my withdrawing and reſerving of my ſelf free, was much to my prejudice, as there be that can bear witneſs; and I could largely make to appear: And he that went on where I left, had it, (as far as I know) at the very ſame rates as I had agreed to, vvithout any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of advantage accruing thereby to me whatſoever. And ſo as I am not, nor never was poſſeſſed of any part or parcel of his Eſtate, either in my own, or under any other Name, ſo I am clear of having <hi>carryed on any private bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain</hi> therein with any one, or of ever having or deſigning
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171621:20"/> a Title-conſideration upon the quitting of that my inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, or upon my Relation to that buſineſs directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly; or of having <hi>under pretences of publike intereſt drove on a deſign of my own private,</hi> (with which <hi>R<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> F.</hi> ſlanders me, pag. 103.) in this or any other buſineſs in relation to the publike, and under covert or pretence thereof; Charge me who can, I here bid open defiance to all the World to prove any ſuch thing upon me during my whole courſe in publike Affairs, in which it is well known, I had opportunities and temptations enough, but alwayes obtained this mercy, to be kept clean in heart &amp; hand from any ſuch thing: And ſo in the preſence and fear of the Lord, whoſe dread was with me, and kept me; I can ſay I came into, and paſſed through, and left all publike imployments, which were neither few, nor inconſiderable; and hereunto I have the anſwer of a good conſcience, even the Witneſs of him who is greater then all, that my life, and all I had, was never ſo dear to me as the Common-Wealth, nor minded in compariſon of it, but for its ſake was put to the ſtreſs, which is now in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement (during this hour wherein all unclean and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirits are let looſe) my rejoicing and exceeding great reward, though of man I have, and do receive the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>But as for <hi>denying ſuch my contract,</hi> its a wicked lye, I have not done it at any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me; nor did I relinquiſh it upon any <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of ſcandal</hi> that either was, or like to be, (as <hi>R. F.</hi> by information, as he ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuggeſteth p. 103.) for I was always clear on the contrary, but for the reaſon aforeſaid, nor did the Committee of Parliament lay it to my charge, <hi>Whether I did contract or no?</hi> but onely put the queſtion to me at the deſire of <hi>Cravens</hi> Counſel in behalf of his Lord, who thought (but he was miſtaken) to have found me a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſer, and ſo to have taken off my Teſtimony in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Common-Wealth; but I was preſent there for the information of the Committee, for which cauſe they had deſired, (not ſummon'd as to a charge) my coming to them by their Regiſter as they did at the ſame time ſeveral
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171621:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> who were eminent members of the Council of State, and of their Committee for Examinations and Diſcoveries when that buſineſs was tranſacted; and Secretary <hi>Thurloe</hi> alſo (who was then Secretary to the Engliſh Ambaſſadors in <hi>Holland,</hi> when the Appeal was made to the <hi>States General,</hi> and their juriſdiction, in the behalf of <hi>Craven</hi> in the caſe aforeſaid, from the juriſdiction of the Parliament of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.)</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that queſtion asked me by the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee as aforeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in my anſwer thereunto; I did neither <hi>ſhuffle</hi> nor <hi>prevaricate with the Committee, nor put off an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer till I ſaw thoſe preſent who were ready to produce the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts out of the book,</hi> (as <hi>R. F.</hi> falſly affirms, as he ſaith, by <hi>information)</hi> they are all abominable lyes, eſpecially the laſt, which I neither ſaw, nor came into my thoughts. And as for the reſt of what thou ſayeſt thou haſt by informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but doſt not mention of whom, and thy Queries whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſaid not ſo and ſo to one in my ſtudy at White-Hall, whom thou nameſt not, when I ſhall ſee any thing relating unto me deſerving an Anſwer under the hands of either of them to whom thou pretendeſt, I may make a Reply.</p>
               <p>To cloſe this particular, Had any thing been in deſign, as <hi>R. F.</hi> and his Confederates would fix upon me, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might have been found then by medling with that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, (which could not otherwiſe be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> expected then to raiſe a clamor) to have anſwered ſuch ends, of which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he nor his Accomplices might have once heard ſo much as a whiſper; but as J was clear, ſo J proceeded bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, knowing that innocency would in the end triumph, and my open contracting at that time was not vvithout reaſon as to the publike, it being a demonſtration to honeſt men, that if J had knovvn any thing but honeſty in the bottom, on vvhich vvas grounded that Judgement, J vvould not have contracted my ſelf for part of the Eſtate vvhich by that Judgement vvas confiſcated.</p>
               <p>As for Major <hi>Fanconer,</hi> J neither knevv him, nor heard that ſuch a man vvas beyond the ſeas, till (after his come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Breda,</hi> vvhere he vvas at the time of the Treaty
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171621:21"/> between the <hi>Scotch</hi> Commiſſioners and their King) he was brought to me to give an account of what deſigns he knew there to have been hatch't againſt the Common-Wealth, which I received according to the Truſt committed to me by the Council in things of that nature; and finding it to be of ſeaſonable and great importance to the ſafety of the Common-Wealth, it being of deſigns generally laid over the Nation, and of ſeveral of the Heads and chief Actors therein particularly in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> (which a few months af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brake forth into an open inſurrection) and it agreeing in many particulars with what I had received from other of my Agents, I gave credit thereunto. And this as J have ſaid, is the firſt knowledge J had of the man, and that which gave the occaſion of my converſing with him; but as for any thing deſigned by me againſt <hi>Craven;</hi> and then ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Fauconer</hi> over the Seas to effect and act it (as hath been whiſpered into the ears of ſome in chiefeſt Authority) or corrupting of <hi>Fauconer</hi> by moneys, or otherwiſe, to ſwear falſly; or any knowledge or apprehenſion that he had in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular untruly depoſed; or putting him upon ſtraits of time, or any other inconveniences whereby he might be ſurpriſed in his underſtanding or memory, or uſing any provocation for that purpoſe, or that he might give in a wrong information, J am <hi>(in the preſence of the Lord who ſhall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing and coming)</hi> clear and innocent.</p>
               <trailer>And thus much in reference to my ſelf.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:171621:22"/>
               <head>As to the STATE.</head>
               <p>THE queſtion in the Caſe is not Whether the Words <hi>Barbarous</hi> and <hi>inhumane Rebels,</hi> were in the Petition of the Officers preſented the King at <hi>Breda,</hi> in which <hi>William</hi> (called Lord) <hi>Craven,</hi> is ſaid to have aſſiſted? or whether what <hi>Fauconer</hi> gave therein, be a true Teſtimony? as that on which the Parliament grounded their Vote of Confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at firſt; and afterwards their judgement for ſale of his Eſtate, (though it hath been the deſign and artifice of his Agents and Advocates (and of <hi>R<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> F.</hi> in particular) thus fallaciouſly to ſtate it, and in proſecution thereof, having got a Verdict of Perjury againſt <hi>Fauconer,</hi> as to that clauſe onely have thereupon founded this loud lying outcry, <hi>viz. That upon the ſingle Teſtimony of that ſcandalous and perjured perſon, the Parliament did give judgement for the ſale of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate;</hi> and have upon this Wheel turned all their late tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions for the retrival thereof, to the undermining the Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and blemiſhing their Juſtice.) But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he the ſaid <hi>Craven</hi> being a Native and Subject of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> did not repair to the declared Enemy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>viz. Charles Stuart,</hi> Eldeſt SON to the late King (then at <hi>Breda</hi> in <hi>Treaty</hi> with the <hi>Scotch Commiſſioners,</hi> for <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtateing of him into the Throne of England,</hi> and where it was agreed to <hi>inſtate him by force of Arms into the ſaid Dominion,</hi> and where many of his <hi>Councellors of State,</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> were met, and were there <hi>hatching</hi> and <hi>laying deſigns</hi> to be acted throughout the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and which afterwards were endeavoured to be put in Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.) And whether he the ſaid <hi>Craven</hi> had not then, and thereat, and during the time of the aforeſaid <hi>Treaty,</hi> and the concluſion thereof, (where it was agreed as aforeſaid) <hi>converſe and familiarity with the ſaid King (the declared ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Common-wealth) in his privy chambers, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and with his Councellors of State, ſelect Juncto, and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers?</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:171621:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> which to do is <hi>adherency to the declared Enemy of the Common-wealth, and conſequently Treaſon by the known Laws of the Land.</hi> And that he the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> hath ſo done, is poſitively proved [to ſay nothing of <hi>Fanconers</hi> Teſtimony, to invalidate which as to what he hath ſaid in this particular, nothing hath yet been offered] not onely by four Witneſſes, <hi>viz. Reyley, Ketchingman, Benſon,</hi> and <hi>Moubray,</hi> ſworn before the Vote of Confiſcation, and in conſideration with the <hi>Parliament</hi> when they reſolved that Vote, but by <hi>Bardſey,</hi> (ſworn before the <hi>Council of State,</hi> and before the <hi>Parliament,</hi> when they ordered his Name to be put in the Bill for his Lands to be ſold) and by <hi>Priſwick,</hi> ſworn before the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations, <hi>Nov.</hi> 18. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>51. and by <hi>Drury</hi> and <hi>Briſco</hi> in their Examinations, which they owned upon their oaths at the Upper-bench on the Tryal of <hi>Fauconer,</hi> where they being produced in <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> behalf as the onely Witneſſes for <hi>Fauconers</hi> convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Perjury, proved his <hi>Delinquency.</hi> And the <hi>Aheren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> aforeſaid to the declared Enemy of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> [thus proved] is <note n="*" place="margin">When I ſpeak of that on which the Parliament grounded ſuch their Vote and Judgement, I ſpeak <hi>Ex manifeſto,</hi> upon what the Teſtimonies themſelves ſay; but as for that which directed every individual member to give his Vote &amp; Judgm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt, and what further Evidence might be of, or amongſt themſelves when they debated and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc't i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, I meddle not with.</note> 
                  <hi>that on which the Parliamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have grounded ſuch their Vote and Judgement,</hi> as aforeſaid, Againſt which and its proof, nothing hath yet bren offered, as J have ſeen or have heard.</p>
               <p>So that <hi>Cravens</hi> Caſe as it is ſtated by his Agents and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates to have been grounded by the Parliament as to the Confiſcation of his Eſtate on thoſe Words, <hi>Barbarous and inhumane Rebels,</hi> and on the ſingle teſtimony of <hi>Fauconer</hi> therein, [on which particular clauſe of his information onely, they have endeavoured to fix a Perjury] withall they have ſaid thereabouts, the clamors that have been made, the noiſes raiſed, are clean out of doors, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt; for neither was the <hi>Parliaments Vote</hi> and <hi>Judgement</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:171621:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> grounded upon thoſe words; nor on <hi>Fauconers ſingle teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony therin,</hi> but otherwiſe as aforeſaid; nor is there any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed at all of <hi>Faucon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> teſtimony to prove that on which their vote, and Judgement was ſo grounded.</p>
               <p>And thus the <hi>Deceptio Viſus, Blind or Foggy Mist of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, and Inhumane Rebbels Corruption, Perjury, &amp;c.</hi> (raiſed to deceive the underſtandings of men, into an apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as if there were never the like horrible <hi>injuſtice,</hi> &amp; <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct proceedings uſed,</hi> and exerciſed) being ſtruck aſide, removed, and diſpel'd, the true and ſubſtantial ground of the <hi>Parliaments Vote</hi> and <hi>Judgement</hi> is apparently to be ſeen, and the reaſon of the juſtice, to every ſober un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: Thus much for the ground.</p>
               <p>As for that which gave the <hi>Parliament</hi> occaſion at firſt to take <hi>Cogniſance</hi> of this matter, and their particular <hi>Votes</hi> thereupon, and the <hi>Appeale</hi> made in his behalfe from the <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> to a forraigne power <hi>viz the States Generall of the Vnited Provinces;</hi> inſtead of addreſſing himſelfe to the <hi>Parliament</hi> in his defence, and the particulars thereof, and this whole buſineſſe, I refer the underſtanding <hi>Reader,</hi> to the relation of them all at large in the Book aforeſaid, intitled the <hi>Lord Cravens caſe &amp;c.</hi> and to the anſwers of the objections raiſed therein on his behalfe; and upon ſerious conſideration of the whole, let ſuch judge; Whether the manner of the Parliaments proceedings therein, be not cleared, as is the ground of their <hi>Judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>For though ſuch an <hi>Appeal</hi> was made (as I ſuppoſe) never the like before was hard of, Arraigning, and charging the Juſtice of the Parliament in their proceedings on that cauſe, and Judgement therein with oppreſſion, and injuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, as grounded on proofe ridiculous, and utterly falſe; or if true, yet frivolous, and not applicable to the cauſe whereon the Judgement was given againſt him: And in caſe that there had been proofe, yet affirming that there is no Law in <hi>England</hi> to warrant ſuch proceedings: And ſo concludeing the Judgement to be unjuſt, and void; And
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171621:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> demanding that the ſame be annulled, cancelled, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked; that the Witneſſes be as perjured calumn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ators, and he put into the poſſeſſion of his eſtate again, alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he was a ſworn ſervant to that State, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be condemned by the Parliament, for his cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, and duty (as he calls it) towards their Lord. And preſſing them thereunto from their uſuall goodneſs in upholding, and aſſiſting the oppreſsed, and for the redreſs of their own honour, and upholding of their power, authority, and prerogative, &amp;c.</q> And though the Laws, of this nation are ſo ſevere, and ſtrict a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as make their Appeals to Forraigne Jurisdictions, from the authority and Jurisdiction of their own Country, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That ſuch Incurre Premunire, which is forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their Liberty, and eſtates, and all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have but life (this crime being in effect a deniall of the ſupremacy of the Jurisdiction of their own Country, and the <hi>Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nateing,</hi> and ſubjecting it in that particular, to that State to whom the Appeale is made.) And, though the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had a full relation of the ſaid Appeale, from their <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>VV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> have here with ſent your Lordſhips an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of my Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>from the juſtice of the</hi> Parliament <hi>of</hi> England <hi>unto the Aſſembly here, which as the papers bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> is intended to be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>livered to us, and which whether it be or not, we do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to take a convenien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> time to Vindicate the honor and power of the</hi> Parliament, <hi>and ſhall do the ſame upon the other Paper, herewith ſent concerning the Queen of</hi> Bohemia; <hi>whereby the King of</hi> Scotland, <hi>is aſſerted likewiſe to be King of</hi> England &amp;c. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Ambaſadors St. John <hi>and</hi> Strickland <hi>in their letter to the Council; dated Hague</hi> May 30. 1651. <hi>Read</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Iune 6. 1651. <hi>In our Letter to the council, you will ſee how the Prince El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r, and my Lord</hi> Craven <hi>have fallen upon the</hi> Parliament <hi>in a [tender] Point; your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will ſee all the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rticulars, and we ſhall in due time do our duty, here to preſent it. In my judgement the Elector, and queen, and Craven have given you a good ground to do more then you reſolved to do, Saith</hi> Ambaſſador <hi>Strickla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d in his Letter dated Hauge</hi> May</note> extraordinary <hi>Ambaſadors</hi> then in <hi>Holland,</hi> by Letters dirceted to the Council of State, and of the States gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall taking <hi>Cognizance</hi> of the cauſe, and aſſumeing Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and authoritie judicially to proceed therein, by receiveing all the Papers concerning the particulars afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid (though for matters onely concerning the Common-Wealth of <hi>England,</hi> and in behalfe of a perſon who was a Subject, Native, and Member thereof) and cauſeing them to be Regiſtred, and permitting Witneſſes to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and examined before them in his behalfe, and in ordering their Commiſſioners, (appointed to Treate with the ſaid Ambaſadors) to deliver the ſaid Paper (wherein
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171621:24"/> amongſt other particulars, <hi>the then King of Scotes</hi> is <hi>affirmed to be King of Fngland)</hi> in the name of the ſaid States, to the ſaid Ambaſadors &amp;c. And though the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament alſo received an account as aforeſaid, of their ſaid Ambaſadors high reſentment, of the ſaid appeale, and the reviveing, and owning thereof by the States, as abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Derogatory, to the Undoubted intereſt, Rights, Power, and Jurisdiction of the Parliament, who have abſolute power, Juriſdiction, and authority of it ſelfe, without depending on any other State, or Prince what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, &amp;c. And of the ſaid Ambaſſadors, anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; ſutable to their truſt, and the Independant Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raingnty, and honor of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> who in ſo high a meaſure were, reproached, and ſlandered with the falſe-hoods, and abſurdities mentioned in thoſe papers: And of their Proteſtation therin againſt the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſaid Papers, and the States aſſumeing the <hi>Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance,</hi> and <hi>Jurisdiction;</hi> And of their Declaration, that it did not in right, or juſtice appertain to them to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle therein &amp;c. And of their demands that the ſaid papers and proceedings thereupon be caſt out, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters thereof vacated, that nothing ſo Degrogatory to the honor, and intereſt of the Common-Wealth, of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> might remain upon their Record to Poſteritie, or <note place="margin">Note.</note> that might give ground to any ſubject, or member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to ſeem to have cauſe to juſtifie any Treaſonable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe againſt it, though a ſworn Servant to thoſe States, out of his duty to the ſaid States, or from any order of <note place="margin">Note.</note> their miniſters, which he, the ſaid Lord <hi>Crav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> had done &amp;c. I ſay notwithſtanding all theſe things, and their knowledge of them; yet the Parliament ordered, and cauſed a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to be iſſued out, Proclaimed and Printed, <hi>July</hi> 3. 1651. for him to make <hi>his perſonal appearance before them on the third of September following,</hi> whereby he had an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertunity to alledge what he had to ſay in his own behalfe. And although he neither made appearance at the ſaid time limited in perſon (it falling out to be the day on which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:171621:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> King of Scots and his whole Army were routed at <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter)</hi> or by Petition ſo teſtified to the truth of his being ſeen to have ſubſcribed it, as might give the Parliament ground to take cognizance thereof, (for there came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it ſo to witneſſe; and therefore the Parliament permitted it not to be read, and if they had, there was no other thing in excuſe in that Petition, but that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be permitted to anſwer by his Friends and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, in regard the preſent conjunction of affairs there did not permit him to come in perſon) yet they took not the advantage to make ſale of his Lands till <hi>June</hi> 22. 1652. above nine months after his ſaid limited day of appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; at which time [and not before] they voted his Name to be put in the Bill (after the reading of his Petition then preſented) for his Lands to be ſold, (the Rents and Profits being only received till then, as is uſual in Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.) And although until the ſaid 22. of <hi>June</hi> there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared nothing before them in defence and excuſe of his not perſonal appearing then as aforeſaid and in his <hi>Petition</hi> then read not a word thereof, <hi>but to be heard by his Council:</hi> Yet upon the <hi>Petition</hi> of his Friends, they took his Caſe into debate again the day before the Act paſſed as a <hi>Law;</hi> and on that very day as it paſſed as a <hi>Law, viz. Aug.</hi> 4. 1652. they conſidered ſomething that concerned the Entail, of part of his Lands, yea upon his own <hi>Petition,</hi> Read <hi>Octob.</hi> 29. 1652. (above two months after the Bil paſt engroſs'd, and his Name therein as aforeſaid) they took in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his tender of a <hi>ſum of money</hi> for the <hi>redemption</hi> of his Eſtate, and debated twice thereupon. But neither then, nor at any time before during the ſpace between the firſt <hi>Vote</hi> of <hi>Confiſcation,</hi> and the paſſing of the <hi>Bill</hi> (which was full <hi>ſeventeen</hi> Months) did they upon any debate take the ſaid <hi>Vote</hi> into conſideration again, but (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the many great <hi>Debates, Overtures,</hi> and <hi>Influences</hi> in his behalf, and the repreſentation of <hi>Fauconers</hi> being convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of <hi>Perjury,</hi> as the laſt and great attempt) did ſee cauſe to <hi>adhere</hi> ſtill to the ſame, and to <hi>rank</hi> his Name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171621:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> other <hi>Delinquents</hi> mentioned in the ſaid <hi>Act</hi> for his <hi>Lands</hi> to be ſold; Upon what weighty reaſons and juſt grounds, the underſtanding Reader may by this time plainly perceive through all the myſts that have been caſt before it; for whoſe right information in the truth of theſe things (of which ſuch a <hi>Dim</hi> is made in the World) as well as for the vindication of mine own <hi>innocency,</hi> and the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the <hi>State</hi> (which <hi>R. F.</hi> in his <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> to <hi>Craven,</hi> tearms <hi>CLUB-LAW,</hi> and ſaith it is <hi>the fortune of the Wars, where many an honeſt man that stands by and means no harm, gets a knock as well as thoſe who began the quarrel.</hi> I have been conſtrained to be thus parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
               <trailer>Thus much as to CRAVEN.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:171621:25"/>
               <head>Secondly, for <hi>Chriſtopher Love.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE man is dead, and in his aſhes, he hath anſwered long ſince the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> and before the <hi>Tribunal</hi> of him who hath with an outſtretched arm deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>England</hi> from the <hi>Trayterous</hi> deſigns, and <hi>Bloody</hi> Plots of him (whileſt alive) and his Confederates. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall ſay little more then I am conſtrained to what is pretended to be by him charged on me before the time of his Execution, chooſing rather by ſilence to be expoſed to the cenſure of ſome, then by replying (how manifeſt ſoever in my juſtification) to ſeem to raiſe my defence upon the Grave of a dead man, who whether he wrote ſo of me as is ſuggeſted, I know not; this I am ſure of, he cannot anſwer.</p>
               <p>But of his <hi>Spirit</hi> alive in <hi>Ralph Farmer,</hi> and the men of this generation, and to the <hi>Treaſons</hi> of him and his <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> and <hi>confederates,</hi> whereof they were attained, (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on preſumption of my having a hand in the diſcovery of which, and bringing them to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> he charges, and ſeeks thereby to prove me not onely a <hi>blood-thirſty, but a blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucking perſon)</hi> I am conſtrained in my own, and the <hi>vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> to ſpeak, and briefly to ſhew,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt</hi> in general; What theſe <hi>Treaſons</hi> are.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly</hi> in particular, how far they reſpect <hi>Chriſtop. Love.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> in general, What theſe <hi>Treaſons</hi> are.</p>
               <p>No ſooner was the breath out of the late <hi>Kings</hi> body, but the men of this generation (who before had ſtrugled ſo much to break in pieces the <hi>Army,</hi> and the honeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt wrapt up in it, &amp; deſperately engaged ENGLAND and IRELAND for that purpoſe) began to entertain thoughts of ſetting up his Eldeſt Son King of ENGLAND, in the ſubverſion and overthrow of the Government of the Common-Wealth, newly declared thereupon, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of love and truth of heart to him and his party, or to ſerve their own Domination and revenge, I leave to him and his Friends to judge.) And the Scottiſh Nation having the ſame Game to play, and not knowing how to effect it otherwiſe then by the diſcontented intereſts and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:171621:26"/> influences of theſe men as an expedient, or third party, (whom they had experienced well enough how to <hi>cajole</hi> &amp; engage under the pretence of a <hi>Kirk</hi> &amp; <hi>Covenant-</hi>intereſt) acquaint them, <q>That they intended to apply themſelves to the King, in which application they would conſider the Presbyterian party in England, as themſelves; and that the Foundation of the Agreement, ſhould be the Covenant; and deſire a conſtant correſpondency, and good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding between thoſe here, and them in Scotland.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>overture</hi> occaſioned the firſt meeting of the <hi>men</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the following <hi>Treaſons,</hi> at which the <hi>gracious diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Prince was ſpoken of, &amp; how that loyalty &amp; the ſence of his ſuffering<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, engaged them to attempt ſomthing in his behalf, if he would cloſe with the Scots and take the covenant;</hi> and this produced the firſt <hi>Treaty</hi> at the <hi>Hague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Treaty bringing forth nothing, the King of <hi>Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts</hi> ſends to theſe men to procure another Treaty between the <hi>Scots</hi> and Him, (as the <hi>Scots</hi> had before for a Treaty with the King) and aſſures them, That if they could obtain it, and the <hi>Scots</hi> to moderate their propoſitions, he would give ſatisfaction to the <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This they take into conſideration, and ſend to the <hi>Scots</hi> to make another application to the King, and to moderate their propoſitions.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> returned, <q>That they would make another application to the King; but withall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſaid it ſhould be upon the ſame Tearms, for that the former breach at the <hi>Hague</hi> had occaſioned rather the heightning of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, then the moderating of them, and deſired them to make uſe of their intereſt with the King to give them ſatisfaction.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon theſe met, conſidered of, concluded, and ſent a Petition to the King for that purpoſe, and Letters to the Queen, <hi>Jerm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> and <hi>Percy</hi> to perſwade the King to give the <hi>Scots</hi> ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Theſe re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urned, <q>That however things ſeemed to them, yet the King was reſolved to give the <hi>Scots</hi> ſatisfaction, &amp; that to that end a Treaty was appointed at <hi>Jerſey,</hi> &amp; <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> adviſed them to ſend one from hence to the Treaty:</q>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:171621:26"/> Furthermore, <q>That if the King and his Privy Council could not agree there, he would remove the Treaty to <hi>Breda,</hi> &amp; at laſt caſt himſelf on the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Commiſſioners.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Accordingly an Agent was pitch't upon and reſolved, <hi>viz.</hi> Capt. <hi>Titus,</hi> who is ſent from theſe to <hi>Jerſey,</hi> and one hundred pounds raiſed amongſt them to bear his charges; Where he ſpake with the King, &amp; <hi>Libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ton</hi> the <hi>Scotch</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, Tels him from what party in <hi>England</hi> he was ſent, <q>repreſents the Presbyterian party conſiderable; had aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance &amp; Letters from the King to the Miniſters, and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian partyhere. That he would give ſatisfaction to the <hi>Scots:</hi> That to that end the Treaty was removed to <hi>Breda,</hi> whither he adviſed them to ſend Commiſſioners, and that he took notice of their non-compliance with the preſent powers.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This Treaty being ended, Capt. <hi>Titus</hi> hearing that the Council of State underſtood that he had been at <hi>Jerſey,</hi> dares not go to England, but ſends a Letter (amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things) for one to come to him to <hi>Callice,</hi> to receive the account of his Agency.</p>
               <p>Upon the reading whereof theſe agree, and ſend one of their confederacy to <hi>Callice,</hi> who having received of Capt. <hi>Titus</hi> the account of tranſactions, returned, and to thoſe who ſent him gives the relation thereof, and the Copy of the Kings Letter aforeſaid, (the original being ſent to Ald. <hi>Bunce</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> for fear of miſcarriage) and <hi>Titus</hi> his Narrative alſo in Writing, which were [all of them] then communicated. Alſo that <hi>Titus</hi> was in debt, having bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed ſome money of <hi>Jermyn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This occaſioned the drawing of a <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> Commiſſion, ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling their Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Parham,</hi> Ald. <hi>Bunce,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor General <hi>Maſſey,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Titus,</hi> to treat in the Name of the Presbyterian party in England with the King at <hi>Breda,</hi> and to aſſiſt their brethren the <hi>Scots;</hi> and when it was moved by ſome, What power they had to ſend a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion? It was anſwered. The King had ſent to them ſo to do, and they had alſo many ſecluded members, whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171621:27"/> they look'd upon to be better then thoſe at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter; which together with inſtructions thereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>next, are ſent by <hi>Maſon, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcy's</hi> ſervant (who came hither on purpoſe to give the King of Scots an account of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and at <hi>Graves-End</hi> had thoſe Papers brought him by three of the correſpondents) Letters alſo were drawn and ſent to the Queen, <hi>Perey,</hi> and <hi>Jermyn, Willoughby, Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey, Bunce, &amp;c.</hi> to forwatd the Agreement, and to act as authorized, and <hi>Titus</hi> had more money.</p>
               <p>The buſineſs being thus put into a likely way of iſſue, private <note n="*" place="margin">No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Faſts were by them appointed to pray for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the Treaty, and for the continuation of the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment afterwards; and <hi>Percy</hi> wrote to them to lend 10000 l. to the King, as that which would add much to the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; with how it might be raiſed, one of the Miniſters moved a way, <hi>viz.</hi> The Miniſters thus to move their friends, <hi>Sir, you ſhall give me</hi> 20, 30, 40, 50. l. &amp;c. <hi>for a charitable uſe, but you ſhall not ask me wherefore;</hi> but becauſe they were not aſſured of the Kings giving ſatisfaction, it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born.</p>
               <p>This Treaty having produced the end deſigned, the King ſends his Letters to ſeveral of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to this effect, <hi>To ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaine the ſaid Miniſters with his Majeſties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with the</hi> Scots, <hi>and with what he would do for ſatisfaction in matter of Religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Government here in</hi> England; <hi>That confidence of their aſſiſtance, was one motive that induced his Agreement: That they would now join heartily with him and the Scots in the endeavour of his reſtitution: And that they having influence (not onely upon their Pariſhes, but alſo on other parts of the Kingdom) would ſtir up not onely their ſeveral congregations, but alſo other places where they had intereſt to join likewiſe with his Majeſty for that purpoſe; and that they would privately pray for him and his good ſucceſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Miniſters to whom to be delivered; to <hi>Edm. Calamy, James Cranford, Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>er Love,</hi> and <hi>VVilliam Jenkins,</hi> to be by them communicated to to the reſt of the Miniſters in and about the City of <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> Miniſters, That if <note place="margin">Note.</note> they could not live quietly in England, they ſhould come to him. Three or four of them alſo he deſired for his Chaplains, and gave inſtructions to his General Agent to treat them civilly, to give * Letters to them, and the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians in the City from him, and to preſs them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:171621:27"/>
               <p> But the <hi>Scots</hi> having got the King into their hands, through the mediation and influence of theſe, and ſo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their ends, deale with them otherwiſe: For though they did prepare (as they promiſed at <hi>Breda) to raiſe armes to put him in the Throne of England;</hi> yet not <hi>Maſſy, Titus</hi> nor the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (whoſe intereſt in the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party in England was made uſe of to bring the King, and them together) were conſidered.</p>
               <p>Of this, <hi>Maſſey</hi> and the reſt complain to thoſe here who very ill reſented it, and thereupon ſent a long Letter to the Kirke, and Committe of Eſtates, complaining thereof, <hi>attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteing it to their pride, laying open in what condition they were;</hi> which with much more was wrote with white ink in a Table Book, and ſent to <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dunbar</hi> Fight followes, after which great Rout (moſt of the Kirke party) the <hi>Scots</hi> being in need of their help, court theſe here again; and the Kirke and Eſtates, and <hi>Maſſey</hi> wrote to them by Sea and Land; <hi>ſignifying the cauſe of the Rout, adviſeing them to stand fast to the cauſe and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, deſireing money, and</hi> 3. <hi>or</hi> 5000 <hi>Muskets and Caſes of Piſtolls; and Maſſey and Titus particularly preſſed for mony, becauſe of their wants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Letters, the correſpondents aforeſaid received, conſidered of, and agreed at that preſent to raiſe about three hundred pounds, to ſend to <hi>Maſſey</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> which the correſpondents performed by 5. and 10. pounds &amp;c. a man, and Letters were alſo by them returned to the Kirke, and Committee of Eſtates, and <hi>Maſſey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon the Correſpondencers begun to have life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <q>the <hi>Scots</hi> preparations to be in the Feild are ſignified hither; advice alſo to thoſe here to Caution, Stedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Timeing of a Party ſeaſonably here, and to write to the Kirke for Union &amp;c.</q> 
                  <q>Theſe here return the ſame Cautions to them, and adviſe <hi>Maſſey</hi> to take heed how he came into <hi>England,</hi> and that he bring with him a ſtrong party:</q> And from <hi>Scotland</hi> came hither returns of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts of the money aforeſaid, and of the Letters to the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171621:28"/> Kirke and State afore-mentioned, how ſeaſonable they were, how much union they effected, how it brake the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns 'of the adverſe Party, and how conſiderable it made them: And waies of ſettling intilligence were alſo ſignified, and made uſe of.</p>
               <p>At length in <hi>March</hi> 1650. 1651. came an anſwer to what was ſignified in the Table Book aforeſaid by Coll. <hi>Bam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feilds</hi> man, which gave an account of the State of <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>land;</hi> and in the ſame Packet, Letters came from <hi>Bayly</hi> (their former Correſpondent, in the behalfe of the Kirke) and from their Lords <hi>Belcaris, Argile Loudoun,</hi> and <hi>Lowthian, wiſhing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m here to give Credit to Bamfeilds Nego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iation</hi> 
                  <q>(in regard he was a <hi>Cavaleire)</hi> preſs for 5. or 10000. pounds in money to buy Armes to furniſh, and Ships to bring over from beyond the Seas into <hi>England,</hi> 5000. old Souldiers; propoſe a Generall to be choſen by theſe here, to command them and promiſe repayment when (as they ſaid) God ſhould bleſs their endeavors ſo as to cauſe a free Parliament in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </q> This <hi>Agent</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with mony in his Pocket, and a Bill of exchange to <hi>Bamfeild.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Preſently upon the comeing of this Packet to them, from <hi>Bamfeild, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>homas Cook</hi> (Generall Agent for the King of <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s</hi> deſigns in <hi>Engla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d)</hi> was taken: Capt. <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter,</hi> (an Apothecary in Blackfryers <hi>Lond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> one of theſe Correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondents) was impriſoned; <hi>Titu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> his Letters and Papers (mentioning the deſigns, agitated by <hi>Bamfeild</hi> in <hi>England</hi> particularly, the 5000. <hi>Souldiers from beyond the Seas as aforeſaid, expreſſing at large, the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rts from whence they were to March; the place on which they were to Land in</hi> England; <hi>the name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f him in a Cypher, who was to command in chief thoſe f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rces;</hi> with Letters from the Marquiſs of <hi>Argyle,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Noble men of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from the Queen concerning <hi>Titus</hi> his <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gotia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ons</hi> from <hi>France,)</hi> were brought (with ſeverall other things) in their originalls by <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> his man to our extraordinary Ambaſſadors in <hi>Holland,</hi> who ſent them to the Councell of State; and <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171621:28"/> divers of his Brethren, and other confederates in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet Juncto of the tranſactions aforeſaid were apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by order of the Councel; upon the aforeſaid, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Informations, and upon the report of a large Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of thoſe deſigns, as they had been traced along by a member of the Council and Committe.</p>
               <p>Theſe apprehenſions, and diſcoveries put a ſtop to the treaſonable proceedings aforeſaid, and gave occaſion for the beginning of New, but of an other nature, <hi>(viz)</hi> the Examining, and bringing to juſtice the <hi>Actors</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as aforeſaid, by order of the Council.</p>
               <p>And not onely was the matter ſo highly Treaſonable &amp; dangerous, but the manner of tranſaction was as <hi>Private</hi> &amp; <hi>Subtil:</hi> For their meetings were upon pretence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Exerciſes; the places either in Shops of Comerce, or Miniſters <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> Studies; The way of communication as of news, <hi>ſeldom any Letters produced in their originalls, but by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyes, and thoſe moſtly in Characters, which for ſome time were kept in a Book;</hi> The perſon from whom it came as ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom asked, (that being generally known,) nor were any to enquire of names, <hi>and the Letters and Papers alſo were before hand put under a Candleſtick:</hi> The contribution of mony <hi>was under pretence of Charitable uſes, for the Widow and O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phans, and poor diſtreſſed Gentlemen beyond the Seas:</hi> This money <hi>generally brought in Baggs, or papers, layd down in Ware-houſes, Studyes, and Chambers, but nothing ſaid when brought, nor any ſeen to receive it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> who agitated, and carried on the Wheele of the deſign, they were men Tenaciouſly fixt thereunto upon a miſtaken <hi>Conſcientious,</hi> and <hi>Religious Principle,</hi> having the Miniſters in greateſt admiration, who were with them in Council, divers of them Souldiers, and ſome of them ſuch as had ſerved in the Army: Theſe trayned up at a <hi>Club</hi> another generation of ſuch as had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Officers, and others where they were inſtructed, and informed as occaſion ſerved, and as it ſeemed good to the former, ſome of whom uſually reſorted thither for that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171621:29"/> purpoſe. A third rank conſiſted of the chief and great men for Purſe, Conduct and Intereſt, of which I ſhall here be ſilent, in regard little as to them, was produced at the High Court of Juſtice; to whoſe proceedings, and what was made there to appear, I have confined for the moſt part what I have hitherto ſaid of theſe Treaſons in the general.</p>
               <p>Secondly in particular, how far they reſpect <hi>Chriſtopher Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Titus</hi> Letter (to ſay nothing of what preceded) ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his fearfulneſs to come into England, and deſiring one to be ſent to <hi>Calice</hi> to receive an account of his Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations in <hi>Jerſey</hi> (as aforeſaid) was read in <hi>his Houſe,</hi> where he was preſent with divers others, and where they conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſend one to <hi>Calice</hi> to <hi>Titus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his <hi>ſtudy</hi> the perſon that was ſent to <hi>Titus,</hi> as aforeſaid, being returned, gave an account of his Journey, where <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> was preſent, &amp; many others, and where was read <hi>Titus</hi> his Narrative in way of a Diary of proceedings at <hi>Jerſey</hi> and the Copy of the Kings Letter, as is before-mentioned.</p>
               <p>There the Commiſſion and Inſtructions to <hi>Willoughby, Maſſey, Bunce</hi> &amp;c. and the Letters to the Queen, <hi>Jermyn, Percy,</hi> were read, debated, and concluded, &amp; when ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate aroſe concerning what Authority they had to give or ſend a Commiſſion, being privat perſons; unto which it was anſwered, The King having ſent to them ſo to do, was Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſufficient. <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> ſaid, <hi>Come, come let it goe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There the Letters were read which were agreed to be ſent to <hi>Scotland</hi> upon <hi>Maſſeys</hi> complaint for their being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected in <hi>Scotland;</hi> there the Letters from <hi>Maſſey,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates, General Aſſembly after the fight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Dunbar,</hi> were read, which deſired Money, Aſſiſtance, Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There he preſſed for the raiſing of Money upon thoſe Letters from <hi>Maſſey, Titus,</hi> Committee of Eſtates, &amp;c. <hi>viz Four or five hundred pounds,</hi> ſaying, <hi>if they would not raiſe it</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:171621:29"/> 
                  <hi>themſelves, they muſt with their Friends; and ſpake to ſome to lend on that account, ſignifying the Contents of the letter, for Money, Arms, &amp;c.</hi> and from whom, which ſum was brought down to <hi>three hundred pounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There</hi> ſome of the <hi>Mony</hi> was brought in, and laid down in his <hi>Room where he was preſent.</hi> There ſome of the Faſts afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid were kept, and he officiated at the ſame Faſts, and at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There</hi> the <hi>Packet</hi> from <hi>Bampfield</hi> was read, (having a Letter [L] on it) the <hi>Letters</hi> alſo from their Lords, <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carris, London, Argyle,</hi> and from <hi>Bayly</hi> their Agent, <hi>moving for five or ten thouſand pounds, for the furniſhing of Arms;</hi> and <hi>ſhipping for five thouſand old Soldiers to be brought from beyond the ſeas, the time when it ſhould be repayed, and for a General to be nominated by them for thoſe Forces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There forty pounds was thought convenient by <hi>him</hi> and others to be ſent to <hi>Bampfield, ten pounds to Bampfields</hi> man was paid, and the other thirty pounds was ſent by Bill of Exchange to <hi>Btampfield,</hi> and a Letter wrote with [B.] on it, brought to Capt. <hi>Potter</hi> for <hi>Bampfield,</hi> and ſaid by the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that brought it, That it came from Mr. <hi>Love, Chriſtopher Love</hi> and another being ſpoken to before to draw up the Letter.</p>
               <p>Theſe are in brief the Treaſons againſt the Common-Wealth, and the manner of their tranſaction, in which <hi>Christopher Love,</hi> his Brethren and Confederates in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and he in particular were concern'd, and for having to do in which he was executed, &amp; unto which Doctor <hi>Drake,</hi> Capt. <hi>Maſſey,</hi> and Coll. <hi>Vaghan</hi> in one Indictment, and Capt. <hi>Potter</hi> in another, upon the arraignment for the ſaid Treaſons at the Bar of the ſaid Court, pleaded guilty, as the Examinations, Papers, Indictments, and Proceedings upon record do make more at large to appear; to which I refer, &amp; to the Book entituled, <hi>A ſhort Plea for the Common-wealth, &amp;c.</hi> Where they are ſet down with their effects, and the Tryal of <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> and his Demeanor thereupon; and on his Examination and Sentence, and his application
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:171621:30"/> to the Parliament; together with the generation this caſe reſpects, <hi>their deportment ab initio, their influence, Number, opportunity and Principles, and the danger of the Common Wealth as to all:</hi> For ſhould I herein be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and draw what naturally would flow from thence, I might fill a Volume; the very confeſſion of one of them <hi>(viz.</hi> Doctor <hi>Drake)</hi> upon his examination, which he gave me with many teares, and which I took from his mouth with my own hand, whereunto he ſigned, being (as I remember) neer twenty ſheets of Paper wrote on the right ſide, and Captain <hi>Potters</hi> as many more.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe through the mediation of the (now) <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector,</hi> whom, and the Army of which he was (then) Generall they had in the higheſt hatred, and ſought to cut of; they received mercy, and pardon from the State, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch their Arraignment, and confeſſion; though ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced to dye, as did the reſt, who were not ſo much as brought to the Barr, though they were ſome of the moſt tranſcendant acts of high Treaſon that records witneſsed to have been diſcovered, brought unto, and proved at Barr of juſtice in this Nation; deſigning and endeavoring by ſecret Plots, and open force the total overthrow, ſubverſion and deſtruction of the Parliament, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Common-Wealth, their Army, friends, yea the very cauſe of Liberty, in which themſelves enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and acted (many of them) in the beginning, worthily in their generations: And for this purpoſe eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſing, falling into, and joyning with the contrary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; <hi>viz.</hi> the King againſt whom they drew the firſt Sword, and vehemently ſounded out the Alarum of war; and with the Queen, whoſe Idolatryes as a Papiſt) they had bewailed publikely on their dayes of humiliation, and charged to be a cauſe of the Plagues on the Nation: And with <hi>Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>myn</hi> and <hi>Percy;</hi> And with the <hi>Epiſcopalls</hi> under whom they had ſuffered ſo much, and of whom they cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out ſo loud, that the ſword was awakened, and taken up to avenge their quarrell: And with all the parties of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171621:30"/> bad men of theſe Nations, whoſe <hi>Wickedneſses, Bloodſheds,</hi> and <hi>Delinquencies</hi> they had publiquely confeſſed: And with <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Rebel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> (for haveing eſpouſed the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, they muſt needs be partakers with the friends thereof, &amp; Carriers of it on againſt whom they declared themſelves to be in the moſt Irreconcileable oppoſition; &amp; with For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, Souldiers ſo highly enveighed againſt by them in the late King, <hi>(viz. the deſign of the Germans Horſe)</hi> and laid to his charge. And laſtly with another Nation, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Scots,</hi> and thoſe People therein, whom they oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at firſt, upon the account of their being for the King; to bring whom, and their King, and all theſe Intereſts together they become the third Party, to which each ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and by whoſe warmth and influence they are all united, and made one, with them they enter into a ſtrong confederacy, and joyntly proceed in the laying of the foundation, and carying on of a New, Deſperate, and Bloody War, wherein thouſands loſt their lives, and the three Nations were hazarded in ſuch a manner, and for ſuch ends as hath been in part expreſt.</p>
               <p>Unto which ſhould I add, how this ſpirit ran generally through the men of the ſame <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>VVhen I ſo ſpeak I do not intend all that are called Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, for thoſe of the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, and Seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſo called, were faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-VVealth; and many of them in armes; nor, all that are called Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for there were divers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Council who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominated, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt this Spirit &amp; thoſe practiſes of ſome to the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inging of</hi> Chriſtophes Love <hi>to juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice.</hi>
                  </note> Principle in this Nation, what deſigns were hatched, how ſubtilly contrived; how deeply plotted, how ſtrongly laid, by the <hi>Cavaleirs</hi> and them (in order to the ſame end) over the <hi>Counties, chiefe Towne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Garriſons, Feild and Navall</hi> Forces there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, &amp; by the Cavaleirs, on the Parliament, and Council of State, and chief members, and Miniſters of each, and of the Army at Land and Sea, (by <hi>Aſſaſſinations, Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Murthers, Fireings, Vio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ences, Blood,</hi> to have cut them off.) What numbers of thouſands of men liſted? What Armes and Horſe provided? What monyes raiſed and how? What Forraign Princes and Forces treated with, engaged and how prevented? What men of <hi>Eſtates Conduct, In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt</hi> concerned? What Armyes formed, how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imed in all things for generall inſurrections to anſwer the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ots</hi> preparations, and motions in the Field, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171621:31"/> their Councils and Motions depending upon, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto the intelligence of the ſtate of theſe deſigned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, whether as to their perfection or irruption (the Army in the mean time abiding the ſharp colds, neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Hardſhips of that naked countrey during the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-ſeaſon, waiting upon their motion and action out of, and from their Faſtneſſes) or ſhould I be particular how they were diſcovered, traced from the beginning, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known all along, and underſtood, with their Agents, Heads, Principals, Variations, Extents and limits, and in the Nick of time when they were known to be ripe, and the time of Execution even come, utterly broken in pieces, (and with that junctures of Providence as well beyond the Seas as in theſe Nations) as were all their Forces in the Field, their King, Nobles, Councellors, great Men, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Miniſters and Soldiers; or could this place admit of ſo large a Diſcourſe, it might prove an aſtoniſhment to the World in the Narration, as the total rout of the other was in the Report and evidently manifeſt that no other thing but the all-ſeeing eye, and outſtretched arm, and tender bowels of the Lord did diſcover, or could deliver the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Council of State, Armies at land and ſea and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt people of theſe Nations from being wholly cut off and deſtroyed, even our Enemies themſelves being Judges; and would prove a warning to all Nations, eſpecially to England (upon whoſe high places in fields of blood, and the ſad cala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ities of many years War it hath been ſorely experimented) to take heed of, and watch over that ſpirit and generation who to effect their tyrannical domination over State and conſcience (to which they would give the Rule, but will not receive it from any) appear not to care with whom, or with what they ioyn, or to what they turn, or how they engage their countrey and themſelves into ruine and deſtruction, under the pretence of Religion and Conſcience, whereas Chriſt Jeſus ſaith, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this world; if my Kingdom were of this world, then would my ſervants fight.</hi> And his Apoſtles and Miniſters declared,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171621:31"/> 
                  <hi>That their weapons were not carnal, but mighty through the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> and propheſied that <hi>in the laſt dayes men ſhould be</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Here are Teachers Traytors.</note> 
                  <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, whereby the laſt dayes ſhould be made perillous;</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes in this very age hath been fulfilled (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) in the men of this generation, with whom I have to do, who notwithſtanding pretend themſelves to be Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt Jeſus and of his Goſpel, and the Succeſſors of his Apoſtles. <hi>O my people (ſaith the Lord) remember what Balaak King of Moab conſulted, and what Balaak the ſon of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or anſwered from Shittim unto Gilgal,</hi> [from <hi>Scotland</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> from <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Scotland<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> from <hi>Scotland</hi> to the <hi>Hague,</hi> from the <hi>Hague</hi> to <hi>England;</hi> from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Jerſey;</hi> from <hi>Jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>da;</hi> from <hi>Breda to Dunbar;</hi> from <hi>Dunbar</hi> to <hi>Fife;</hi> from <hi>Fife</hi> to <hi>St. Johnſtons;</hi> from <hi>St. Johnſtons</hi> to <hi>Worceſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>] that ye may know the righteouſneſſe of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far of theſe <hi>Treaſons</hi> in the general, and how far they reſpect <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> in particular, the effects of them, and proceedings thereupon: In the rehearſal where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (through this urgent and neceſſary occaſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have been the rather thus particular, that <hi>thoſe who are concerned</hi> may be <hi>awakened,</hi> and look out ere it be too late; for if this <hi>ſpirit</hi> which but the other day was ſtruck down with ſuch an aſtoniſhing ſtroke from heaven, as the like thereof hath not been heard of in theſe later ages, be ſo far alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy recovered out of its ſwoune, &amp; gathered into ſuch life &amp; confidence as that it dares to appear thus openly in the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of them in whom it ſo work't &amp; acted (as it hath in this <hi>R. Farmer's Libel)</hi> ſtiling them <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus, Servants of Chriſt whoſe Names are yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the Churches,</hi> [as are the Expreſſions, pag. 110.] and <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> aforeſaid (a chief deſigner and actor of them, for which he was beheaded by ſentence of the High Court of Juſtice) <hi>as a man moſt innocent, falne into the hands of Huck-ſters,</hi> of whom it ſaith, <hi>Ile ſay nothing of the man, I need not, he was well enough known in England, in his death,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:171621:32"/> 
                  <hi>bewailed of thouſands, and his Name precious with many godly,</hi> [as are the very words, pag. 110.] and the detecting, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining, and bringing thoſe their unparallel'd Treaſons to Juſtice, <hi>Rancour, Malice, Spightful, and moſt cruel proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Blood-thirſtineſs, Blood-ſucking, ſucking and ſwallowing the Bloods and Lives of men, Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> [as the ſame page hath it.] And the taking notice of his not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraying the leaſt grudging or repentance of his death for any thing acted therein, (though ſuch were his actions as aforeſaid) <hi>a going about moſt unchriſtianly to undervalue, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe and diſparage that comfort and confidence he profeſſed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy at his death, a killing of his good Name, and endeavoring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly to kill him twice, and the latter with more cruelty then the former;</hi> with ſuch like, as it is ſet down pag. 106, 107. And the diſcovering of thoſe his, and his other fellow-Traytors Treaſons, a <hi>Trappanning;</hi> as it is termed pag. 105; 106.) and ſpending ten pages thereabouts, and in reviling and abuſing the <hi>State</hi> and their Miniſters in the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, and doing Juſtice thereupon, which I ſhall no further repeat: I ſay, If this <hi>Spirit</hi> be ſo gotten head thus above-board, in print to manifeſt it ſelf, even whileſt thoſe are in <hi>Rule</hi> whom it ſought to cut off, and who were made the <hi>Battel-Ax of the Lord, and his Weapons of War,</hi> to the hewing down, and cutting in pieces the men in whom it appeared and acted. What under-ground-work (upon ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional grounds) may hereby ſtrongly be ſuſpected to be forwarded and near perfection? The tender eye of the Lord hath watched over and his outſtretched arm deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed England (as hath been ſaid) from its <hi>devilliſh</hi> contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and <hi>bloody</hi> Workings, through the <hi>rolling of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Garments in blood,</hi> and multitudes of other ſharp and ſore extremities of <hi>War,</hi> as the effects thereof: Let thoſe who are concerned look to it now; out of a deep <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>This I felt &amp; wrote before the ſecond Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with an intent to have publiſhed it a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> their coming together; but their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ting was ſhort, and their diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſudden; and ſome workings were diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and I ſtop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the publication.</hi>
                  </note> ſence upon me do I give them warning; Who may alſo take it into conſideration, Whether ſuch an <hi>infamous Libel</hi> as this is, wherein the proceedings of <hi>Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ament,</hi> the <hi>Council of State, Committee for Examinations, &amp;c.</hi> and their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171621:32"/> 
                  <hi>Miniſters</hi> in caſe of the former, are ſo highly reflected upon, charged and reproached with ſuch horrible <hi>indirect dealings, corruption</hi> and <hi>injuſtice;</hi> and their deliberate <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> therein, expreſly tearmed <hi>CLUB-LAW,</hi> (the higheſt affront that can be given to an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament) The fortune of the Wars, &amp;c.</hi> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent</hi> himſelf, to whom it is dedicated for Patronage, as to a <hi>worthy</hi> and <hi>conſiderable perſon,</hi> under the Name of <hi>Right Honourable, A lover of his Countrey;</hi> wherein the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of them all in the caſe of the latter, is called <hi>Trapan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſpightful and malicious proſecutions, &amp;c.</hi> (and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent execution done by ſentence of the High Court of Juſtice authorized by Act of Parliament, (in which the whole body of honeſt men to the intereſt of the Common-Wealth and the Army, (all of whom thoſe Treaſons ſought to deſtroy) are concern'd) <hi>Blood-thirſtineſs, blood-ſucking of a man,</hi> intimated as one <hi>moſt innocent, faln into the hands of Hucksters, &amp;c.</hi> (For theſe Acts of Juſtice were the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and the proceedings therein had, were in, and by vertue of their <hi>Authority,</hi> in order to the ſafety of the <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> and nothing was done by me but by vertue thereof, in the diſcharge of my Truſt, wherein I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, and have <hi>the anſwer of a good conſcience,</hi> ſerving my generation in uprightneſs of heart: And what is ſaid, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns and ſtrikes at them and their Authority who gave the Judgement and the Sentence which ſo much troubles them, and by whoſe Power they were acted, though the direction be at me, at whom it is revengefully flung, ſuppoſing it their ſafeſt courſe, &amp; that for ſo doing they have now their day and liberty, as is plain to any ſober underſtanding.) And laſtly, Wherein that <hi>Treaſonable</hi> ſpirit which plotted the deſigns, raiſed, embodyed, and carryed on thoſe deſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and cruel <hi>Wars,</hi> as aforeſaid, is <hi>warm'd</hi> and <hi>cheriſhed:</hi> I ſay, Thoſe who are concern'd may conſider whether it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts with their Honor and Reputation, and the Juſtice of the good and wholeſom Laws of the Nation, and due eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and regard they would have given to their own
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171621:33"/> Acts by the generations to come, and with the ſafety of the Nations, to permit ſuch an <hi>infamous libel</hi> to paſs up and down without a reproof.</p>
               <p>By this time the ſerious <hi>Reader</hi> may plainly perceive who is the <hi>blood-thirſty</hi> and <hi>blood-ſucking</hi> perſon, that can <hi>ſuck and ſwallow the bloods and lives of men;</hi> Whether I who had (with others as aforeſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) to do in the examination and diſcovery of thoſe Treaſons which had their influence to the actual ſhedding of the blood of Thouſands, and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly ſought to ſwallow the lives of the Parliament, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, Army and its <hi>Friends</hi> in theſe Nations: Or <hi>Ra. Farmer</hi> who hath thus appeared in the juſtification of theſe Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and calls the bringing of one [a chief] of them to execution, and of others to the Bar of Juſtice, <hi>a ſwallowing of the bloods and lives of men, blood-thirſtineſſe, and blood-ſucking?</hi> Whoſe are the <hi>malicious, moſt ſpightful,</hi> and <hi>cruel proſecutions,</hi> whether mine (as he preſumes) in order to the bringing ſuch Blood ſucking Treaſons to light (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my duty) and blood-thirſty Traytors to Juſtice; or his in ſeeking to <hi>kill my good Name,</hi> (which is far out of his reach) and to render me as vile a perſon as any under Heaven, upon his preſumption of my ſo doing? Who are the <hi>Miniſters of our Lord Jeſus?</hi> Whether thoſe who Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably deſigne by Warre and Blood, the ruine of their Countrey, and the overthrow of a Common-Wealth, and this in oppoſition to the Cauſe and People they once enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in, and with, and in the behalf of the contrary, and all its Abettors and Aſſiſters; or thoſe whoſe Goſpel was <hi>Peace on Earth, and good will towards men?</hi> Who are the Churches of Chriſt? Whether ſuch in which <hi>prayers were made for Kings and thoſe in Authority, that under them they may lead a peaceable life, in all godlineſs and honeſty;</hi> or thoſe in whom the <hi>Memory</hi> of them are ſaid to be <hi>pretious,</hi> who conſpire the overturning and deſtruction of the Government, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they might lead a <hi>peaceable life in all godlyneſſe &amp; honeſty,</hi> and for that purpoſe had of them full liberty and large protection? And laſtly, Whoſe <hi>Name ſhall rot &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:171621:33"/> 
                  <hi>or if it be remembred, it ſhall be with abhorrency &amp; deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Whether mine whoſe actions have been as aforeſaid, in the diſcovery of thoſe Treaſons, or <hi>R. Farmers,</hi> who in the behalf of thoſe Treaſons and his Brethren, hath thus appeared and acred?</p>
               <p>Thus much of his Charge in general, and of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of <hi>Christo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her Love,</hi> and his Brethren and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and his ſpirit, (now alive in <hi>R. F.</hi> and that generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) in whoſe behalf I am thus charged and accuſed, and in diſcharge whereof I have been conſtrained thus to draw them forth as a LOOKING-GLASS for the PRIESTS, and an AWAKENING to ENGLAND.</p>
               <p>The ground of the Charge as it is laid down pag. 106. is this.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Viz. That I was a zealous proſecutor of</hi> Chriſtopher Love, UNTO, yea AFTER <hi>death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>After death,</hi> (for with this he begins, as that which it's like, he ſuppoſeth he can moſt poſitively prove, and may beſt ſerve his purpoſe) and for this his onely inſtance is the Book entituled, <hi>Mr. Love</hi>'s <hi>Caſe;</hi> of, and concerning which he ſaith, and peremptorily chargeth me in theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words.</p>
                  <p>That you were a zealous proſecutor of Mr. <hi>Love</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, yea, and after death, is ſo manifeſt, that as impudent as you are, you will not deny. That you proſecuted him after death, appears by what you publiſhed againſt him when he had no being to anſwer for himſelf; wherein you endeavour maliciouſly to kill him twice, and the latter with more cruelty then the former, killing his good name, &amp; what in you lyes, making him a reprobate and an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt from God and Glory. I ſuppoſe you will own that piece called Mr. <hi>Love's Caſe,</hi> printed by <hi>Peter Cole<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> (as wel as the other Books you publiſh't againſt him) wherein you go about (moſt unchriſtianly) to undervalue, debaſe and diſparage that comfort and confidence he profeſſed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy in, and at his death, and this upon ſeveral accounts, which I will not recount to avoid tediouſneſs; one onely
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171621:34"/> Ile mention to ſhew your ſpirit of envy and bitterneſs; It is the Animadverſions upon the firſt Section, pag. 34. Mr. <hi>Love</hi> (ſay you) it's more then probable was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vehemently exhorted, encouraged, importuned, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſolemnly by all the ſacred Intereſts of High Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, conjur'd by his Clergy Companions, to dye like a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and reſolute Champion of the Cauſe, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray the leaſt grudging of any fear, or repentance for any thing he had acted upon the ſervice thereof, leſt it ſhould be ſaid of Presbytery, Her glory was ſtained and betrayed by the Cowardize of her Fitſt-born. And pag. 38. Here we have the ſecond part of the Theatrical Flouriſhes of Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> confidence—Much might be animadverted, but I forbear. You have a ſtrange ſpirit that his comforts and confidence in God trouble you. And then you go on to charge him with hypocriſie and lying, and other baſe imputations all along, beſpattering and beſpotting, and beſullying him (as you can) even to his laſt. I know what ſlight touches of charity you have now and then; and at the cloſe of that Pamphlet, which are inconſiſtent with that you had charged him before, as that he acted the part of a moſt unchriſtian Calumniator upon the Scaffold in the very approaches of death, pag. 38. but pag. 46. You moſt unchriſtianly reproach him and his Doctrine, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, Whereas in purging himſelf [he means Mr. <hi>Love]</hi> from the aſperſion of lying, he ſaith thus, I hope you will believe a dying man, who dares not look God in the face with a lye in his mouth; intimating (ſay you) as if his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to dye was a bridle in his lips to reſtrain him from lying. The truth is according to that principle of his, That he who once truly believed, can never by any ſin or wickedneſs whatſoever, loſe the love and favour of God.—His being ready to dye, in conjunction with a perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Saintſhip, ſhould rather be a temptation upon him to lye, or commit any other wickedneſs, then an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement upon him to refrain lying. Thus you. I have done with that; but I pray that you may find more favor
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:171621:34"/> and mercy from God, then he found from you, and to that end let him grant you Grace to repent of theſe ſpightful and moſt cruel perſecutions.</p>
               </q>
               <p>This is his <hi>Charge, Inference,</hi> and <hi>Concluſion,</hi> and every word of it, which is a lye in every particular, a heap of lyes and falſhoods; therefore I deny it all, though he is ſo bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen-fac't as to ſay of me, <hi>viz. As impudent as you are, you will not deny it:</hi> For I am ſo far from having wrote the Book aforeſaid, entituled, <hi>Mr. Loves Caſe,</hi> or from having the leaſt hand therein, that I do not certainly remember that ever I read it over; but write it I did not, nor had I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hand in it, nor do I know who is the Author thereof; yet how poſitively, and with what confidence doth this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Lyar affirm it mine? how oft? about twenty times he falſly charges it on me) with what bitter invectives and reflections, and with what heigth of impudency and zeal, as one whoſe life is concern'd and touch't, and ſuffers in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very word ſpoken of, or thing done to that his dear Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſober may plainly read in theſe his Expreſſions? And by this ſingle inſtance (had I ſaid, or ſhould I ſay not a word beſides) ſuch may judge, Whether ever man of a more <hi>impudent face, flinty forehead, ſeared conſcience, vile</hi> and <hi>lying ſpirit</hi> hath appeared in Print? And whether he <hi>fears God,</hi> or <hi>regards man,</hi> or cares what he ſaith or doth, or is to be believed in any thing he affirms? This is <hi>Ralph Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> This is <hi>my Enemy without a Cauſe.</hi> This is he that writes againſt <hi>Perfection,</hi> of <hi>Satan enthron'd in his Chair of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and then calls it <hi>Quakeriſm in its exaltation;</hi> of the <hi>Impoſtor dethron'd;</hi> and ſtiles it <hi>The quakers Throne of Truth detected to be Satans ſeat of lyes;</hi> of the <hi>Rottenneſſe</hi> (as he blaſphemouſly reproaches) <hi>of the quakers converſion and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the general, exemplified in this</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>buſie Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, in ſpecial inſtanced in his practiſes againſt the Estate of the Lord Craven, life of Mr. Love;</hi> who ſaith, <hi>By occaſion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this Truth is aſſerted,</hi> viz. <hi>If we may judge of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, honeſty, and perfection of the quakers in general, by this man in particular, a man be as vile a perſon as any under hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:171621:35"/> 
                  <hi>and yet a perfect quaker.</hi> [Whether I or he be the man of whom the ſubſtance of this may be ſaid, and on whom it is found? Reader judge.] This is he that ſo abominably ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, reflects upon, and traduces the Acts and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the higheſt Judicature and Court of Juſtice in the Nation, in the moſt weighty executions (one of them) as <hi>England</hi> hath brought forth; and ſo highly reproaches the proceedings of them, their Council of State, Committee, Court of Juſtice, and Miniſters aforeſaid. This is <hi>Cravens</hi> Advocate, in whoſe behalf he reviles and abuſes (as hath been ſaid) in hope of, and in order to the retrival of his Eſtate, and then dedicates it to him for Patronage, in a Light, Lying, and Frothy Epiſtle. This is the Champion of <hi>Edmund Calamy, Chriſtopher Love,</hi> and his Brother Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Confederates as aforeſaid, and of them called <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, whoſe Names</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>are yet precious in the Churches.</hi> This is he, for the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aring teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whoſe deceit, and ſpeaking and writing in the Name of the Lord, many have ſuffered long impriſonments, and ſome have been whipt. This is he that hath poured forth all this filth &amp; rage at me, that talks of making <q>An Agent in the Marches of Wales; of the Machivillian Maxime, LYE, Calumniate, ſlander, and do it boldly and with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and ſome of it will ſtick; it will take with ſome or other of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Proverb, <hi>If all enter not yet hal will;</hi> of a common-lyar, a ſhameleſs fore-head, a profligate ſpirit, a moſt ſupernaturally and God-forſaken hardened heart and ſeared conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Ralph Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mer</hi> who calls himſelf <hi>A ſervant of that Joſus Christ who was crucified at Jeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alem</hi> 1600 <hi>yeers ago<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whoſe blood</hi> (he villanouſly &amp; falſly ſaith) <hi>the quakers</hi> (who witneſs it and its cleanſing) <hi>trample under foot</hi> (this inſtance proves it true of himſelf, <hi>as a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mmon thing;</hi> and who is called, and calls himſelf a Miniſter of the Goſpel: A Miniſter of the Goſpel! get thee gone to thine own place, the Goſpel denyes thee; the children of Light ſpue thee out. No marvel after all his Trades, he took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him this Name, and turned thither to ſhelter him; doſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:171621:35"/> thou ſay to me, <hi>Turn Turk, man, or become a Jew, to whom</hi> [thou ſayeſt] <hi>the Name and Goſpel of Chriſt, and Chriſtian is odious?</hi> Turk and Jew ſhall riſe up in Judgement againſt thee, &amp; ſhal condemn thee: This is ſome of the ground-work on which (he ſaith, pag. the laſt) his Diſcourſe and Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very is founded, and that he is well aſſured that it will ſtand firm; and thereforeſaith, <q>As for any farther Anſwers, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, contendings, or debatings with them or him, I declare this as my <hi>Coronis,</hi> my farewel to quakeriſm.</q>
               </p>
               <p>What ſayeſt thou now <hi>R. F.?</hi> Were they <hi>No babes in the world, and yet honeſt;</hi> [as thou expreſſes, pag. 106.] Who adviſed thee to theſe things?</p>
               <p>Thus much of the proſecution of <hi>Christopher Love</hi> after his death, (the killing him after he was dead) moſt falſly charged upon me as aforeſaid, by this Lyar <hi>Ralph Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For thoſe before his death, he ſaith, page 108.<hi>—As for the perſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion of him in his l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and of his Tryal, I ſhall not enter upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry of—</hi>So (as to proof) that's given up, as the other is taken down: Where is then the hypocriſie with which he chargeth me for accuſing the Prieſts, and him in particular, with <hi>Blood-th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ineſſe, the More</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, before I had pulled out th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m (blood-thirſtineſſe, blood-ſucking) in mine ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>? I ſhall not enter upon the ſtory,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet in the next page 109. he enters upon the ſtory of that, upon which he ſaid before he ſhould not enter, and ſpends ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral pages therein, ſaying (to palliate the matter) <hi>I ſhall not</hi> (as I ſaid) <hi>engage to the whole of your proſecutions againſt him,</hi> when as he hath ſaid no ſuch words, but the contrary, viz. <hi>I ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er, &amp;c.</hi> So his own hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing proves him a lyar, a belyar of his own Record: Doth not, wil not this man ſay any thing? Well, ſeeing he wil enter upon the ſtory, &amp; that he chooſes rather with his own Pen to Regiſter himſelf a falſe man to poſterity, then to miſs it, What's then the part of my proſecutions (as he ſaith) againſt him, to which he will engage (for it concerns
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:171621:36"/> me to ſift this matter) and in what pieces finds he it? Why <hi>in a Book written and publiſhed</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>by Mr. Love himſelf,</hi> (and yet) <hi>finiſhed</hi> [but] <hi>the last day but one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his death: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Title of it thus, A clear and neceſſary Vind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, &amp;c.</hi> What is that to me to prove proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Why, <hi>I deſire you</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>to take notice that there is a lying Pamphlet put forth, entituled, A ſhort Plea for the Common-wealth; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n which there are many groſs lyes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in things that rela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to me.</hi> Well, what of all that? Why (ſaith this liar pag. 111. 112.) <hi>He ſuppoſes Capt. Biſhop wrote the lying Book.</hi> He ſuppoſes! Suppoſition is no proof nor ſufficient ground to charge, nor reaſonable matter for a Reply; nor ſhall I therefore make any thereunto But to come nearer the matter, (and to ſearch thy bowels R. F. (they are the words of thy Epiſtle) <hi>for a real diſcovery, that the world may no longer be deceived with a windy concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.—)</hi> If <hi>Chriſtop. Love</hi> did ſuppoſe I wrote it (and ſo ſayeſt thou, page 111. and alſo the words which thou ſayeſt are his, page 113.) Then how comes I (in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeration of thoſe pretended lies, and the obſervations thereupon ſaid by thee to be <hi>Chriſtop. Love</hi>'s) to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly charged therewith, page 111. in theſe words,<hi>—Another thing he charges him with, is a loud lye, &amp;c.—</hi>and page 112.<hi>—Where he further ſayes, he</hi> (Biſhop) <hi>charged him, &amp;c.</hi> no leſs then four times in the ſpace of twenty eight lines, page 111, 112. Doth he charge me poſitively by name? Now either theſe words are <hi>Chriſtop. Loves</hi> (as is ſaid and pretended) or <hi>R. Farmers?</hi> If <hi>Chriſtop. Loves,</hi> then he is one while ſaying <hi>he ſuppoſes,</hi> at other times ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely <hi>charging</hi> what before he only ſaid he <hi>ſuppoſed,</hi> and ſo he is not to be believed in what he ſaith (in that his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended book) No, not as the words of a <hi>dying man;</hi> and if his words when dying be ſuch, <hi>at which time</hi> R. F. ſayes, <hi>what ever I ſay, men are moſt ſerious, and to be believed;</hi> what are they when he is not in that condition, and how to be accounted? If they be not <hi>Chriſtop. Loves</hi> (which I incline to believe) then they are <hi>Ra. Farmers</hi> forgeries
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:171621:36"/> ſoiſted after his death, into (what he ſaith are) the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of him, who h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> accounts his dear friend, and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, finiſhed <hi>the laſt day but one before his death,</hi> for whom he ſeems to be as zealous as for his life; and being ſo <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, foyſted,</hi> and <hi>ſophiſticated,</hi> they are not to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or taken as <hi>Chriſtop. Loves</hi> writings, but as <hi>R. Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> forgeries, and ſo not to be believed or anſwered. Thy malice at my good name <hi>R. F.</hi> drew deep, when thus to beſpatter it, thou plungeſt thy ſelf into this Labyrinth. But to proceed a little further, What are thoſe lies ſaid to be in the ſaid Pamphlet, ſo ſuppoſed to be mine, and ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved? Why, <hi>It will not,</hi> ſaith <hi>R. F.</hi> page 111. <hi>be to any purpoſe to ſet down the particulars, becauſe my Reader hath not the book whereby to judge of the truth or falſhood, I ſhall therefore content my ſelf to give you what obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Mr.</hi> Love <hi>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es on the man, and his lying ſtories.</hi> If this, viz. to give the obſervations, and not the thing, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe the concluſion, and not the premiſes; to charge ſo and ſo, and yet to be ſilent wherein, on purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; if this, I ſay, be fair dealing, fit matter to reply unto, or ſufficient proof of ſuch a charge, let the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yea my enemies themſelves be Judges.</p>
               <p>Is there any more yet? Yea, but like the former; <hi>They</hi> viz. his NO BABES<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. aforeſaid, <hi>adviſe me to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d a book concerning Mr.</hi> Loves <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſigns, and his death, written and pen'd by you, and they ſay it will give the Reader further ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction: But you have dealt as craftily in the printing of this as of the former, printed ſo few, &amp; kept or given ſo at your own piſpoſe that I cannot get it,</hi> page 106. Which being a lie, and the book neither nam'd, nor got<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor ſeen by him, and it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the pretended further ſatisfaction therein, being but matter of <hi>hearſay,</hi> and that from his <hi>No Babes, &amp;c. (they did adviſe, they ſay)</hi> I ſhall paſs it by as falſe and frivolous, and not deſerving a reply.</p>
               <p>Thus hath this liar ruſht, as the horſe into the Battel with his<hi>—But yet what I finde from other pieces, I have met with in this matter.</hi> (What matter? the Antecedent is—
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:171621:37"/> 
                  <hi>who did Trepan Mr.</hi> Love, <hi>and ſome of that party?</hi> the pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (and J have mentioned all of them) ſay nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and of nothing nothing can be found, nor nothing met with) <hi>I will communicate to yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and the world; and this the rather to ſhew you; what a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hypocrite y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u were in charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us Priests (as in</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">I call ye not Prieſts in ſcorn, (its a lie, ſcorning I deny, and therefore thee and thy Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of ſcornets) but <hi>Prieſts</hi> ye are by profeſſion, who are Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and yovr old Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination was by the name of <hi>Prieſt.</hi> And tbe Common-Prayer-Book hath it <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Clerk.</hi> And page 37. in a ſcorning manner thou ſayeſt of thy ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; <hi>Is it not pity that any man (much more a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and if you will, a Prieſt) ſhould, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſcorn you call us) with blood-thirſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and my ſelf in particular, as in Title of your Pamphlet; you ſhould have pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m out of your own eye, before you reproacht us with a mote in ours. I ſuppoſe, here I have done, though it be partly done already, you will appear to be not only a blood-thirsty, but a blood-ſucking perſion.—</hi>I ſay, thus hath he ruſht into this caſe, as the horſe into the battel; but to what diſadvantage, the ſober by what hath been ſaid, may eaſily perceive: For neither hath he or any of his pieces ſo much as looked towards the matter, viz.<hi>—Who did Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan Mr.</hi> Love, &amp;c. which muſt be the matter, or what he ſaith is inconſiſtent, and non-ſenſe. Nor hath he made ſo much as one thing hitherto to ſtand as a beam or mote of <hi>blood-thirſtineſſe,</hi> or <hi>blood-ſucking</hi> in my eye, as to any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of <hi>Chriſtop. Love, before</hi> or <hi>afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> his death; the work it ſeems he aimed at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erga Verſa,</hi> but hath thus miſt and hit himſelf; ſo what he ſaith he hath found, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to me and the world from the other pieces; which he ſaith he hath met with in this matter, ſhews what a hypocrite himſelf is, not me and an abominable vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who hath charged me with <hi>blood-thirſtineſſe,</hi> and <hi>blood-ſucking,</hi> (and committed ſuch wickedneſſe in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution thereof) as a <hi>mote in my eye,</hi> but makes no ſuch thing to appear, and hath not firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or at all, <hi>pulled the beam of blood-t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irſtineſſe</hi> (charged and proved, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, that's a <hi>lye</hi> by me on him, and his Generation of Prieſts, which he hath not otherwiſe then by this Recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination attempted to diſprove) <hi>out of the eyes of himſelf and generation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I might conclude this caſe, for ought unto which I am obliged any further to reply. But foraſmuch as <hi>Ra. Farmer</hi> hath expreſly charged me with <hi>practiſes of</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:171621:37"/> 
                  <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgery</hi> in theſe Words, <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>z. I ſhall diſcover the ground of your ſo eaſie an entertainment of the thoughts (at leaſt ſuggeſtions) of forgery in me, from thoſe practiſes of forgery which I ſhall declare to have been really acted by you, pag.</hi> 106. And for that the <hi>Committee</hi> for Examinations, and one of the Members thereof in particular is accuſed, reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſcandalized, as well as my ſelf, as in that his (as he calls it) Declaration thereof. And becauſe the deſign of what is ſo ſaid is to blemiſh the credit of what ſhould be made publike of thoſe Treaſons on the behalf of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth, which the Author ſuppoſed would be, and therefore ſo ſpeaks, and ſollicitouſly beſeeches the Reader not to believe any thing that ſhould ſo be made. And in regard the Charge relates to my truſt, and therein as to the lives of men, leſt I ſhould ſeem to any to decline ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing becauſe of guilt, or to take advantage by the diſ-repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of another to cover what may be thought my own; I ſhall ſpeak to both his inſtances, <hi>viz. Chriſtopher Love,</hi> (though parcel of the foreſaid attainted vindication) and the nameleſs Letter, [though it come forth ſo, and on the ſingle credit of this Lyar, ſoften by me proved Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate.]</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The firſt is this, <hi>viz.</hi> That whileſt he was examined, he faith I did put in ſix or eight lines into his Examination, which he never ſaid, I ſuppoſing he would be ſo meale-mouth'd as not to read it, or to put his hand to my Forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry without any more a-do; but that he did [to my ſhame] make me blot out at leaſt ſix lines in his Examination, which was but very ſhort; and that ſome of the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee did ingenuouſly ſay ſometimes, That he did not ſpeak ſuch Words as I had put in; and that he did refuſe to put his hand to it, ſeeing he was abuſed by me, but told them if they would give him a copy of it he would ſubſcribe his hand; but that they denied him a copy, which made him to ſuſpect they did not intend to deal fairly with him, as he found true after. And then goes on to ſhew where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in [ſayes this Lyar, but gives no inſtance, yet ſaith] and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:171621:38"/> that to their conviction; &amp; concludes thence thus, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech the Reader not to believe any thing that ſhall come forth, either pretended to be my Examination, or the Examinations of other men againſt me; they are but the Forgeries and Contrivances of Mr. S. and Capt. <hi>Biſhop,</hi> pag. 113. And further, That the Examinations of the Witneſſes were taken from them in private, and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched together by Mr. <hi>S.</hi> and Capt. <hi>Biſhop,</hi> That they were not aſhamed to produce them and read them in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen <note n="*" place="margin">And why not in open Court, the Witneſſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring it, and referring ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto (the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars being many &amp; lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>) and the Court allowing it?</note> Court. That ſome of the Witneſſes had ſo much <note n="†" place="margin">Capt. <hi>Potter</hi> being the firſt Witneſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, bogled at what he had wrote, and ſigned, and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t from the Tower; but upon his arraignment pleaded guilty to it all; what honeſty he had left that ſo did, let wiſe men judge.</note> honeſty left, as to diſavow them in open Court; and therefore (ſayes he again) believe nothing but what was ſworn in open Court, nor all that neither; for ſome of the Witneſſes ſwore falſly as [he ſaith] he made <note n="*" place="margin">He being (as I remember) touched with the words concerning the Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Come come, let it go;</hi> fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>w out in a rage, and ſaid, That he was againſt the going of it, or words to that effect. Whereby he diſcovered himſelf to be in the principal part of the deſign, of which himſelfe profeſſed, and others would account him inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</note> appear in his Defence, pag. 110. And that becauſe he was belyed about his Examination before the Committee, and may be more abuſed after he is dead; therefore he was neceſſitated to diſcover that jugling and baſeneſſe of Mr. <hi>S.</hi> and me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his Examination, which he thought [as it ſaith] ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have made publike, pag. 112. And thus this Lyar brings all this in.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Among all theſe lyes thus generally hinted, I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved one in ſpecial, wherein Mr. <hi>Love</hi> chargeth him not onely with lying, but alſo with forgery, pag. 112. And concludes, <hi>And well might</hi> Mr <hi>Love think how this</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>injur'd other men,</hi>
                  </q> and that in the like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind, pag. 112.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:171621:38"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Vind. Chriſtopher Love</hi> being apprehended by vertue of a Warrant from the Council of State for High Treaſon; and being brought before the Committee to be examined, before any queſtion was demanded of him as to the cauſe of his apprehenſion aſſigned in the Warrant, he volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily made ſuch a deep and general profeſſion of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, (as to the Treaſons which afterwards were charged upon, and proved in Court againſt him, and in part by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf confeſt) that the Committee were at a ſtand how to ask <hi>ſuch an innocent profeſſor any queſtion of guilt;</hi> and ſo unto him they declared: Whereupon he (ſuppoſing (it's like) that he and his actions were hid from them, and lay in the dark.) gathered ſpirit, and ſaid in theſe, or words to this effect, <hi>Gentlemen, I look upon you as honourable perſons, ask me any queſtion in particular, and I will ingenuouſly anſwer you, as I have made a general profeſſion.</hi> Hereupon I put to him (as from the Committee) ſome queſtions concerning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; correſponding with the cauſe of his apprehenſion, aſſigned in the Warrant aforeſaid, which giving him to ſee that the Committee was within his Vail, Inſtead of making an ingenuous, or any anſwer thereunto, he fell into a great paſſion (being cloſely touch't) and particular reflections, and refuſed to anſwer, ſaying <hi>he would not accuſe himſelf, and that it was the High Commiſſion Court.</hi> It was anſwered, That it was not the High Commiſſion Court, for he was not put to anſwer to interrogatories upon his oath, to accuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf when none did or could accuſe him; which was the High Commiſſion Oath, <hi>Ex Officio,</hi> condemned by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: But he being in cuſtody, and accuſed of ſuch High Treaſons, and informations being ready to be produced (and I then brought forth two) relating to the matter whereof he ſtood charged, and unto which he was deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to anſwer; by the ancient Law of England he ought to anſwer, YEA or NAY, thereunto, which was what the Committee required of him. Then he was demanded as to other Correſpondents in the ſame Treaſons: To which he anſwered, <hi>He would not be an Informer.</hi> This his neither
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:171621:39"/> anſwering to the queſtions demanded againſt himſelf, nor as to others, though he had ſaid, <hi>Ask me any queſtion and I will ingenuouſly anſwer;</hi> and made ſuch a general profeſſion of innocency as aforeſaid; I ſay, This and his other high and peremptory carriage occaſioned many Words to paſs between the Committee and him; ſo that there was not ſuch a proceeding in ſetting down his Examination, as was uſual in ſuch caſes by the Committee, <hi>viz. The queſtion lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely put, and wrote down, and read, and then the Anſwer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and wrote, and then read and expeſſed, and altered as the Priſoner deſired, before another queſtion was asked.</hi> But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt the much ſpeaking I took notice of ſome few things which he ſaid, and having wrote them (after the heat was ſomewhat over) read it in the hearing of him and the Committee, to the end that he might have it expreſt, alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or changed to his ſatisfaction, (as was uſual to every one that was examined, before he be required to ſet his hand thereunto;) upon the hearing of which read, he liked not ſome part thereof, whereupon I ſtruck it out, and drew his Examination as he would have it, and then read it, which he not objecting againſt, the Committee required him to put his hand thereto; but he refuſed to ſign it except he might have a copy thereof, which they thought not fit to grant without an order from the Council, it being not uſual in caſes of Treaſon otherwiſe to do: So he was returned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cuſtody of the Serjeant at Arms, without having ſigned his Examination, which (for the contents of it) was not material, nor was any uſe made thereof at his Tryal. This is the truth of the matter.</p>
               <p>Now whether ſo to take, prepare and draw an Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the preſence of the Committee, and the ſight of the Examinant, and with ſuch changes and alterations as the Examinant doth deſire, (ſuppoſe I had miſtaken in ſome Words or Expreſſions, as eaſily I might (but do not grant) conſidering the manner of the Examination as aforeſaid) be Forgery, Jugling, Baſeneſſe? Or whether it be Mr. S. and my B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeneſſe, Jugling and Forgery, or a diſcovery
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:171621:39"/> thereof, who neither dictated to, nor adviſed with me, as to what I wrote? Or whether this or any other paſſage mentioned in this caſe makes to appeare, or proves that whatſoever ſhall come forth as the Examination of him, <hi>[Chriſtopher Love]</hi> or the Examinations of other men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, <hi>are but the forgeries</hi> [as he ſaith] <hi>and contriv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Mr. S. and me, patch't together in private,</hi> and ſo not to be believed? Or, Whether the bare ſaying of theſe Words onely, <hi>Which made me ſuſpect they did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to deale fairly with me, as I found true after: And then goes on</hi> [ſayes <hi>R. F.] to ſhew wherein, and that to their convic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> [but how or in what, <hi>R. F.</hi> ſayes not] be ſufficient to ground ſuch a charge upon the Committee, as of <hi>unfair dealing,</hi> or makes manifeſt wherein they dealt ſo unfairly with him, or convicts them thereof? Or whether the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne and end of all this, be not apparently to juſtifie <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> as innocent, and to render the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and thoſe that proſecuted and gave judgement againſt him, guilty of his blood? And whether ſuch things ought to be ſuffered, I leave to the ſober to judge, and thoſe who are in Authority to conſider.</p>
               <p>Had the Examination been perfected, and he ſet his hand thereunto, and committed to my cuſtody, and ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards have inſerted any word or ſentence that he had not ſign'd, without his knowledge or conſent. This indeed had been <hi>forgery</hi> in me; &amp; I [had I ſo done] deſerved indeed to have been made a publike example; but no ſuch thing did I, nor doth this Inſtance accuſe me of any ſuch; nor did I ever exerciſe in ſuch things as theſe, otherwiſe then a good conſcience, <hi>doing unto all men</hi> [therein] <hi>as I would they ſhould do to me,</hi> and alwayes abhorring the contrary as a moſt abominable Wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>my putting in ſix lines into his Examination which he never ſaid, ſuppoſing he would be ſo meal-month'd as not to read it, or to put his hand to my forgery</hi> (as he ſlanders) <hi>without any more ado.</hi> It is falſe, and a thing (in the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of wiſe men) not likely by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be ſuppoſed,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:171621:40"/> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> That he would ſign what I had wrote (as ſaid by him in his Examination<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being concern'd as to his life, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch a ſtir as he did) without reading of it, or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt what was wrote by me, as ſpoken by him which he had not ſaid, had any ſuch thing been: Nor was any ſuch thing, as to put what was not his, as his Examination, upon the ſuppoſition aforeſaid, or any other conſideration, ſo much as in my thoughts; nor did I any thing of which I was aſhamed, or that deſerved it, but the contrary: Nor do I remember that any of the Committee did ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes that he did not ſpeake ſuch Words as I had put in, (though they by reaſon of his paſſion and prevarication, and the Words it occaſioned, not taking ſuch notice of his expreſſions as I did, who minded them as my buſineſs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, &amp; ſet down might expreſs themſelves, as not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring in ſom things that he ſo ſaid; &amp; himſelf by reaſon of his raſhneſs, might forget; &amp; not liking when he was come coolely to conſider what was wrote as ſaid by him, might deny his own expreſſions; whereby it doth not follow, That what I took as his, was not by him ſpoken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to ſuch effect.</p>
               <p>Thus much to his <hi>firſt</hi> inſtance, and of the paſſages at the Examination of <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> in which I have hitherto been ſilent, and thought not to have made it publike, but <hi>R. F.</hi> having ſo highly charged me and the Committee in this Caſe, pag. 110, 112, 113. and falſly concluded thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pag. 114, 115, 116. I am conſtrained thereunto for my own, and their neceſſary vindication.</p>
               <p>The ſecond follows in theſe Words; <hi>I have one inſtance more under: he hand of a godly, reverend, and faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel now in being, well known to moſt of the inhabitants of this City, and many in London ſo to be, who writes to me, That being to be queſtioned about M.</hi> Love's <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs,</hi> (as he was, &amp; impriſoned) <hi>Biſhop</hi> (ſays he) <hi>was Clark to the Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ee of Examinations, and wrote down all that I ſaid, &amp; add a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vers things, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ereby endeavouring to enſnare me, for which I ſharply reproved him, telling him that I knew</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:171621:40"/> 
                  <hi>his Birth and Breeding, and therefore I did ſcorn to be ixami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by ſuch a one as he was, at which both he and the Commit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tee were much offended, threatning to uſe much ſeverity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, but the Lord reſtrained them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vind.</hi> What's this to the purpoſe, as to <hi>Forgery?</hi> to prove which on me it is produced, (taking it as it is, and for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that it is ſo, as is expreſſed) it ſaith, <hi>I wrote down all that he ſaid;</hi> It doth not ſay that I wrote down more. And ſhould I not have wrote down all he ſaid? What crime is this? Is this <hi>Forgery?</hi> How doth malice render him void of underſtanding? For the paſſage, <hi>And added divers things, there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y endeavouring to en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nare me;</hi> it manifeſtly appears by what immediately follows, that it intends Words ſpoken by way of Examination, not an addition of Words which he ſpake not, inſerted into his Examination; which latter (had it been ſo) would have ſuted his Caſe, not the former; it ſeems the queſtions prick't him to the quick, that he was ſo wroth at the applying of them, that the Committee ſaw cauſe to threaten to bind him (ſo much he was from it) to the <hi>good-behaviour</hi> and that the ſubſtance of the queſtions was ſuch truth, and ſo applicatory to him in the behalf of the Common-Wealth, that he reckons the propoſing of them matter of Enſnarement; that is to ſay, if he had anſwered to the queſtions as he could, he ſhould have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt what was demanded. <hi>And added</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>divers things, thereby endeavouring to enſnare me.</hi> What a pittiful genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have I to deal with, and how ſottiſhly malicious?</p>
               <p>Now as to the ſtory, I remember that <hi>Matthew Havi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſometimes of <hi>Briſtol)</hi> being in cuſtody as a Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of <hi>Chriſtopher Loves</hi> Treaſons, and brought before the Committee to be examined thereabouts, manifeſted much filth and rage at me (but in what particulars I do not perfectly remember) becauſe of ſome queſtions that I put that nearly touched him, for which the Committee ſharply reproved him, as he deſerved, <hi>who knew not a bridle for his tongue, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et profeſt himſelf to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel.</hi> Notwithſtanding I was ſo far from being provok't
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:171621:41"/> thereby to do him harm, that I (conſidering him as a frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, peeviſh, inconſiderable, ignorant weak man, and drawn in through ſimplicity rather then deſign) accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht (of mine own accord) his liberty from that which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe might have proved hard upon him; for at ſome of the meetings aforeſaid, at <hi>Chriſtopher Loves</hi> he was, for which there was proof.</p>
               <p>If this be the man that wrote the pretended nameleſſe Letter aforeſaid, and if he ſo wrote as this Lyar hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, let the reaſonable judge whether he hath returned me well for that my moderation and voluntary kindneſſe: And whether ſuch a one be a <hi>Godly, Reverend, and faithful Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſter of the Goſpel,</hi> (as R. F. Epethites) who is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to expreſſe himſelf under his hand ſuch a <hi>Scorner,</hi> as that he ſcorned to be examined by ſuch a one whoſe birth and breeding he knew, and this in ſuch a manner as that the Committee by reaſon thereof were <hi>much offended and threatned</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>to uſe much ſeverity againſt him;</hi> and what a one R. F. is, who calls ſuch a ſcorner, <hi>a godly, faithful Miniſter of the Goſpel,</hi> and a <hi>Revere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,</hi> (and bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to print it) whereas of the Lord onely it is ſaid; <hi>Holy and Reverend is his Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are his inſtances, and yet thus this impudent Lyar concludes, pag. 114. <hi>Oh horrid and dreadful! Not onely to be a common Lyar, but to forge, to put in, and to add words on purpoſe to enſnare men. No marvel you catch at Faucon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers words but once ſpoken, and put them in haſtily to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ones Eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, when you forge and put in words, many words, (whole lines in a ſhort Examination) which were never ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and this to take away m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns lives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But where are (all this while) thoſe <hi>practiſes of forgery,</hi> which thou ſayeſt thou ſhalt declare to have been really a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by me, as proof of what thou haſt affirmed, and as a plain and juſt ground for thoſe thy concluſions? Doth all that thou haſt produced, prove one practice or tittle of <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery really acted by me?</hi> Do thy inſtances bear thy conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? [Let the impartial judge.] Or diſcover they any
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:171621:41"/> thing more then thy falſe and ſlanderous ſpirit, who careſt not what thou ſcrapeſt together, and ſayeſt, nor mindeſt thou how it and thee may ſtand before the Judgements of Wiſe men, ſo it may but ſeem to reflect upon, or any ways prejudice (as thou thinkeſt) my Name and Reputation. My Truſt was great, laid upon me, and faithfully paſſed thorough in as dangerous and difficult a ſeaſon as Englands Common-Wealth hath known. Thou haſt charged me <hi>Ralph Farmer</hi> expreſly, (but very falſly and maliciouſly, as hath been made to appear) with <hi>practiſes</hi> (as thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt) <hi>of forgery really acted by me,</hi> with the <hi>putting in, and adding words, many words, whole lines in a ſhort examination, which were never ſpoken, on purpoſe to enſnare men, to take away mens lives; the lives</hi> (as thou ſayeſt) <hi>of Miniſters of the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus,</hi> in the Caſes of High-Treaſon, whileſt I was in the exerciſe of that my Truſt, and to the high abuſe and breach thereof. Therefore how canſt thou but expect another manner of reckoning with thee for the Vindication of my innocency from theſe, and thy other charges and ironical expreſſions of <hi>Corruption</hi> and <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect dealing,</hi> as to <hi>Perjury</hi> for the <hi>taking away of a mans Eſtate,</hi> during, and in relation to that mine Employment, then what is made in theſe few ſheets of Paper, which to check thy lies and ſlanders, I have at preſent thus ſent forth into the World.</p>
               <p>And whereas thou ſayeſt, <hi>I ſhall diſcover the ground of your ſo eaſie an entertainment of the thoughts (at leaſt ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions) of forgery in me, from thoſe practiſes of forgery, &amp;c.</hi> Thy ground and diſcovery is every way falſe; neither have I really acted practices of <hi>Forgery,</hi> nor haſt thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon me any one ſuch practice; nor was any ſuch thing the ground of my ſo eaſie (as thou ſayeſt) an entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the thoughts of <hi>Forgery</hi> in thee; but thou having publikely declared and profeſſed in the Epiſtle to thy <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Enthron'd, &amp;c.</hi> concerning the matter of thy Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in theſe Words, <hi>viz. And this I can and do faithfully aſſure the Reader, that here</hi> (in the ſaid Narrative) <hi>is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:171621:42"/> 
                  <hi>of the one, or the other, but what is real truth, as will be made good upon any occaſion.</hi> And I finding upon peruſal of that Narrative, that in the rehearſal of a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal paper and part thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> the Letter of G. F. to J. N. taken upon him, thou hadſt thus ſet it down, <hi>The Light of Chriſt in you all I AM—</hi>and in the Margin over againſt it, the Word <hi>OBSCURE,</hi> as a ſpecial note of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to the Reader, to give him to minde the import thereof; and upon comparing thoſe Words ſo affirmed and plighted by thee, with the original under G. F.'s own hand-writing, (which I had by me, and out of which I wrote what was ſo taken) that the Words were not ſo but theſe, <hi>viz. The Light of Chriſt in you all I OWNE—</hi>upon conſideration thereof, and the vaſt material difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe two words, <hi>AM,</hi> &amp; <hi>OWNE,</hi> in the ground, eſpecially in that place, and how they turn the ſentence, and of the dangerous tendency of that alteration to the life of G. F. (in that ſeaſon) as a high Blaſphemer, and thy noting him thereby to be ſuch; and of thy bold-thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and cruel ſpirit manifeſted in that thy Pamphlet. I ſay, upon conſideration of all theſe things, I did in my Anſwer charge thee with <hi>Forgery,</hi> and expreſſed my ſelf as thou haſt repeated, <hi>viz. You may here ſee of what a falſe and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rit this Prieſt is, and what a devilliſh wickedneſs it is to forge in ſuch a wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d; as for it, were it tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ſo, would take away a mans life: What credit is to be given to what ſuch a one ſaith? Is not he that can do this paſt bluſhing? Is there any wickedneſs ſo great that ſuch a one may not be well conceived to be ready to act? Is ſuch a one a Miniſter of the Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l? Words needs not further to expreſs ſuch an act, which in its very f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ce is ſo manifeſtly wicked and abominable; A wickedneſs not found in the Roll of thoſe evils which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle mentions ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> make the laſt dayes perillous.</hi> This was my ground of charging thee with Forgery, and this is part of the concluſion I drew from thence, which whether it be not ſubſtantial, and bearing what I have inferr'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, or whether thine of me be like it in the caſe, let underſtanding men judge.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:171621:42"/>
               <p> Thus much in <hi>vind cation</hi> of my innocency, from this <hi>lyars</hi> charge of <hi>forgery;</hi> there are yet ſome queſtions laid in my way, to remove, ere I cloſe my vindication as to this part of his Libel with which he begins, and with which he ends, and in which he wraps it up, and by which his ſpirit is further made manifeſt, and the ground and concluſion of all <hi>Edmund Calamy,</hi> and his <hi>Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The firſt</hi> Queſtions <hi>are theſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <q>
                     <p>I was deſired to ask you, who did trepan Collonel <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> into a deſign, for which he loſt his life, when as he had given over all thoughts of engaging, till he was moved thereto by a Trepanner, as he declared before his death?</p>
                     <p>;And who it was trepanned Sir <hi>John Gell</hi> into a miſpriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Treaſon?</p>
                     <p>And laſtly, Who did trepan Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> and ſome of that party? Theſe queſtions are propoſed by thoſe who are No Babes in the world, and yet honeſt; and they ſay this <hi>Biſhop</hi> can (if he will) give ſatisfaction in: You know <hi>George</hi> what theſe things mean, and I know what the laſt means; and they adviſe me to read a book, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> deſigns, and his death, written and penn'd by you; and they ſay it will give the reader fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfaction. Thus this <hi>lyar</hi> begins the caſe of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Love;</hi> and theſe are the very firſt words therein, as they lie together, not a vvord omitted, page 105. 106.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The laſt</hi> Queſtions <hi>follow.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <q>
                     <p>But let me ask you, Were theſe all whoſe blood you thirſted after? Did you not write a Letter to a friend of yours in <hi>Briſtol</hi> from <hi>White-Hall,</hi> that until <hi>Calamy,</hi> and ſome others of the Prieſts were dealt withal as <hi>Love</hi> was; it would never be vvell? I hope I ſhall one day get that book of yours, which you wrote againſt him, (mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:171621:43"/> before) viz. A ſhort Plea for the Common-wealth. Thoſe who have ſeen it tell me, it moſt fully ſets forth the fierceneſſe and bitterneſſe of your ſpirit, not only againſt him, but that you ſhew your rancour and malice therein againſt many of the ſervants of Chriſt, whoſe names are yet precious in the Churches, and the memorie of whom ſhall live, when your name ſhall rot and periſh; and if it be mentioned, it ſhall be with abhorrencie and deteſtation as infamous as poor <hi>Fawconers</hi> is. Thus he ends, page 115.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Replie. This is the head and the tail of this <hi>Bloody Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> (whoſe bellie I have alreadie cut out) and the feet on which it goes,—viz.<hi>—I was deſired to ask you who did Trepan, &amp;c. by thoſe who are no Babes in the world, and yet honest; theſe queſtions are propoſed; and they ſay this</hi> Biſhop <hi>can give ſatisfaction in, and they adviſe me to read a book, &amp;c. And were theſe all whoſe blood &amp;c. Did you not write a Letter? &amp;c. that until</hi> Calamy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here's the middle and both ends brought together: I ſhall proceed preſentlie to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch the two ends as the middle, and ſo finiſh this caſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt; the aforeſaid <hi>Collonel Andrewes,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Gell,</hi> were the earlie men of this generation, who conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt the Commonwealth, one of whom, viz. Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Androws</hi> their High Court of Juſtice cut off, which ſtroke, and that upon <hi>Chriſtophrr Love, &amp;c.</hi> (it ſeems) this <hi>lyar,</hi> and his <hi>No Babesin the world, and yet honeſt fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and call the diſcoverie of their treaſonable conſpiracies a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panning of one into a deſign, for which he loſt his life, and the other into a miſpriſion of a Treaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> and his <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>Confederates</hi> were the nex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, who were diſcovered to take up where they left, and to deſign and act the Treaſons aforeſaid, for which <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> was beheaded, as hath been declared. This he and his <hi>No Babes &amp;c.</hi> call a trepanning likewiſe.<hi>—Who did trepan Mr.</hi> Love, <hi>and ſome of that party,</hi> ſaith he; ſo that in the Treaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, he and they were, &amp; the root of the matter was in them, otherwiſe into what were he and they trepanned?
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:171621:43"/> and why is it demanded who did trepan, &amp;c.<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> How comes he and they then to be innocent men, and all the ado afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid to be made in their juſtification, the lamentation of his death, and the admiration o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them as precious? Doth not this <hi>lyar</hi> and his <hi>No Babes,</hi> &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hereby ſhew themſelves to be <hi>No Babes</hi> in wickedneſſe? Do they not ſhew themſelves to be in the ſame ſpirit, and one with what that ſpirit brought forth? Thoſe who are concerned may hereof take notice, and conſider, whether the diſcoveries of ſuch high Treaſons, and the eminent execution of Juſtice on ſome of the chief actors therein, ſhould be thus publikely arraigned, and groſſely abuſed, eſpeciallie by one who pretends him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel. Is not the <hi>Armies</hi> fighting againſt, and deſtroying thoſe who appeared in the field to act the ſame, and of as high a nature as the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and execution of ſome of thoſe, by Sentence from a Court of Juſtice who conſpired the action? Can the one then be reproached and traduced; and the other clear? Sithence the <hi>cauſe</hi> was one and the ſame, and the enemy, and the end of his deſignes, and the deliverance to them who fought in the field, as to thoſe who ſate at the Stern. And this I ſay to the <hi>Army,</hi> either lay down the cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and confeſs your ſelves guilty of all the blood ſpilt in the war, or let that be reproved as it deſerves, which thus ſpits in the face of it, and of you, and of thoſe who acted with you, and of their Authoritie and Juſtice from whence you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived your Commiſſion.</p>
                  <p>Next, conſider the ground, bottom, and foundation of all theſe clamours of this <hi>lyar,</hi> and his high accuſations of me, as aforeſaid: Is it any thing of his own knowledge, or that he hath ſeen, or read under my hand, or doth he name his Informers, or adviſers? Nay, <hi>but I was deſired to ask you who did trepan? &amp;c. Theſe queſtions are propoſed by thoſe who are</hi> No Babes, <hi>&amp;c. and they ſay this; and they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe me to read a book, &amp;c. but I cannot get it, and th y ſay it wil give the reader ſatisfaction, &amp;c. I hope I ſhall one day get that book, &amp;c. thoſe that have ſeen it tell me ſo and ſo.</hi>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:171621:44"/> 
                     <hi>And let me ask you, Did not you write a Letter, &amp;c.?</hi> This and ſuch like is all that he hath produced as certainty in this whole matter, and whethet it be a ſufficient ground, bottom, and foundation [or indeed any at all] for ſuch his clamours, charges, and accuſations, let the reaſonable judge.</p>
                  <p>Laſtlie; in anſwer to the <hi>Queſtions,</hi> to the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,</hi> I had nothing to do in the execution of Collonel <hi>Andrewes,</hi> nor the miſpriſion of Collonel <hi>Gell,</hi> nor in the diſcoverie of either of their Treaſons, nor in that whole buſineſſe, nor can I give ſo much as a particular account of them. So this <hi>lyar</hi> who hath asked, and thoſe other who he ſaith deſired him to ask theſe queſtions of me, (on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to render me as a perſon who hath made it my trade thirſtinglie to deſign the ſhedding of the blood of men, and the ruining of eſtates) have ſhewn themſelves what <hi>No Babes</hi> they are in malice and wickedneſſe, and how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinglie diſhoneſt, not only thus to inſinuate, but to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that I can, if I will, give in this ſatisfaction; and how impudent this <hi>lyar</hi> is, as to ſay poſitively to me, <hi>You know what theſe things mean: That is to ſay,</hi> that I am the man that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>repanned them, as aforeſaid, and that I do know my ſelf to have thus deſigned, who am thus free, as hath been declared</p>
                  <p>To the <hi>third;</hi> I know not of any man that in the behalf of the Commonwealth, either tempted, or drew forth [nor do I believe any did] the Treaſons aforeſaid, which ſecretly lodged in the diſcontented breſts of <hi>Chriſtop. Love,</hi> and his Brethren, for ought I know [and I am perſwaded] his and their own ſpirit was the father and mother of thoſe Conſpiracies; or [to give them their own word back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain] the <hi>Trepannor</hi> of them all: Nor if his boſom friend, who was as his Confeſſor before his death cannot, do I gueſs who of his generation, or any other, can give ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to this <hi>queſtion,</hi> except this <hi>lyar</hi> who asks it, though he ſaith, <hi>I know what this laſt meaneth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the <hi>fourth;</hi> I neither thirſted after the blood of theſe,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:171621:44"/> nor any man; but theſe and all other who thirſted after the blood of the Common-Wealth, and not onely endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but put theſe Nations into War and Blood to effect it, I ſought to diſcover, as was my place and Truſt, and their deſigns for that purpoſe; upon which diſcoveries ſome of the chief of them were brought to Juſtice, whereby the ſpilling of blood was much prevented, my heart being more tender to the blood and being of a Common-Wealth (ſuch a one as England) and the hundreds of thouſands of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent perſons therein, that it might be preſerved, then to one man who ſought and deſigned its ruine and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and to me he that by deſign, counſel and contrivance, effects that which ſheds the blood of men, though he draw it not with his own hand, is a Murtherer in a higher degree then he that violently doth the execution; And <hi>whoſo ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed, for in the image of God made he man,</hi> is the Law of God, unto which agreeth that of God in every mans conſcience.</p>
                  <p>Now in caſe of the Treaſons aforeſaid, there was one patticular which put it out of the capacity of pardon, viz. <hi>The aſſuming unto themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſupreme Power within the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdction of the Common-wealth, to give Commiſſion and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to divers perſons, authorizing them to treat with a forreign State,</hi> (the Scots) <hi>and the proclaimed Enemy to the Common-wealth</hi> (Charls Stuart <hi>King of</hi> Scots) <hi>for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of him by force of Arms into the Throne of England; which Treaty they effected, and at which Treaty it was ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluded, from whence ſprang the War aforeſaid:</hi> Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing a moſt <hi>tranſcendant</hi> Act of <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>king at the very Root of the <hi>Authority</hi> then in bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, (for it's impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that two Supreme Powers in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Common-Wealth can conſiſt; and if that War had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>compliſhed the ſaid reſult of the Treaty, the Common-Wealth had not been) the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> ſaw it not onely juſt, but neceſſary for the ſafety of the Common-Wealth, to make it exemplary in his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:171621:45"/>
                  <p> To the fifth and laſt, I wrote many Letters when I was at <hi>White-hall,</hi> and much buſineſs was upon me and went through my hands, it is impoſſible for me to remember preciſely all that I wrote ſo many years ago; nor do I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member whether I wrote the matter of this Queſtion, but this I ſay, Produce my Letter, and what I wrote I ſhall not deny; in the mean time, and for the cloſe of this caſe, let <hi>Edmund Calamy</hi> and his Brethren take heed, leſt what this Lyar hath queryed concerning him and them, they prove it to be a truth. It's good advice, however it be received, from him who knows what he ſaith, and wiſhes no evil to him or them, or any man; but an <hi>irreconcileable Enemy is to the ſpirit of darkneſs, which worketh in the dark by deſign, war, and blood-ſhed, to ſet up its own dark domination over State and Conſcience;</hi> of which (even of his and their generation, as hath largely been made to appear) England hath been of late made deeply ſenſible.</p>
                  <p>And now <hi>R. F.</hi> let me ask thee one queſtion, <hi>Is not the hand of Joab in this buſineſs?</hi> were not <hi>thoſe of Chriſtopher Loves bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren &amp; confederates</hi> (who were lately at <hi>Briſt.) thy No Babes, in the world, and yet honeſt,</hi> (or ſome of them) <hi>by whom thoſe queſtions aforeſaid were propoſed,</hi> and who deſired thee to ask them of me, and adviſed thee as aforeſaid, or from whom, or by whoſe intimation, or direction, or inſtigation thou haſt charged, wrote, and reviled as aforeſaid? <hi>Are not theſe thy Rowers, and have they not brought thee into deep waters?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus much of the Caſe of <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> and in <hi>vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Proceedings and Judgement of Parliament, and their Miniſters, in the Caſe of him, and of the ſaid William</hi> (called Lord) <hi>Craven, from the ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndalous allegations, and iro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ical reflections of this Lyar R. F.</hi> in his <hi>Libel</hi> aforeſaid, as to both, and in <hi>conviction of his falſe charges therein of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to Fauconers Information, and other indirect dealing in the Caſe of the one, and of blood-thirstineſs, blood-ſucking, &amp;c. in the Caſe of the other,</hi> and of all his mire and dirt caſt up at me in the management of each, on purpoſe to render me (if he could) the vileſt of men: Upon ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:171621:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> of all which, the wiſe and ſober may judge whether his <hi>Exemplifications</hi> (as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>earms it) prove me to be ſuch a man as he hath repreſented me to be, or the <hi>rottenneſs of the</hi> (people called) <hi>Quakers converſion and perfection in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> as he blaſphemeth; or that I am the <hi>buſie Biſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> (in medling with that which I ſhould not) as he affirmeth; or whether that be a <hi>truth</hi> which (he ſaith) <hi>by occaſion of my practiſes in ſpecial instanced againſt the Eſtate</hi> of the firſt, and <hi>life</hi> of the laſt, <hi>is aſſerted, viz. If we may judge of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, honeſty, and perfection of the quakers in general, by this man in particular, a man be as vile a perſon as any under hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and yet a perfect quaker,</hi> as his Title-page, and other parts of his Libel hath it: Or whether I have not proved this to be a truth; <hi>viz.</hi> If the conſcience, honeſty, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Miniſters of England in general, may be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>Ral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h Farmer</hi> (and what he writes) in particular, a man may be one of the vileſt of men, yea a notorious traytor, and yet a profeſſed Miniſter of the Goſpel. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Whether by any thing he hath ſaid, the Declaration of my innocency in the Caſe of <hi>Craven,</hi> is impeach't or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict?</p>
                  <p>Thus much in reference to the firſt part of this Rejoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for the reſt of his ſtuff as to the caſes aforeſaid, I reckon it not worth any further Reply<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but do leave it to fall with its foundation, which is thus raced down, and overturned.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>WHITE-HALL, May. 1652. <hi>So much of the Examination of Coll.</hi> Edward Drury, <hi>as relates to the buſineſs of</hi> Craven.</head>
               <p>HE ſaith, That whilſt he was at Breda; he, this Examina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, and ſeveral Officers of the King of Scots, as Lievt. Coll. <hi>James Bardſey,</hi> Capt. <hi>John Briſco,</hi> Capt. <hi>Tho. Hutt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Capt. <hi>Tho. Hunt,</hi> Major <hi>Rich. Fauconer,</hi> and others, to the number of five or ſix and twenty, did joyn together in a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the King for ſome relief, which Petition was drawn
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:171621:46"/> by Major <hi>Richard Fauconer</hi> in this Examinants Lodging, the reſt of the Officers being preſent, which was to this effect, May it pleaſe your Majeſty, the great ſence we have always had of your Majeſties preſent condition, hath been the prime cauſe of our long ſilence; but now our neceſſities are grown ſo great and unſupportable, that we are inforced to petition or periſh, moſt humbly deſiring your Royal Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to take into your Princely conſideration their extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties who have been alwayes ready to proſtrate their lives in his Majeſties Royal Father his ſervice, &amp; are no leſs willing &amp; ready to proſecute the ſame in what your Majeſty ſhal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; Moſt humbly petitioning your Royal Order that ſome courſe may be taken for our preſent ſubſiſtance, that our future endeavours may not be buried in that unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble calamity which our known Loyalty hath reduced us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; And We ſhall cordially pray.</p>
               <p>After this Petition another Memorial was wrote to the King, to this effect, May it pleaſe Your Majeſty, We whoſe Names are ſubſcribed, humbly deſire your Royal Warrant in order to your gracions Promiſe to Mr. Secretary <hi>Long,</hi> that when the Money was brought in by the Scotch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, We ſhould be relieved, and that the poor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Breda</hi> who have preſerved us from periſhing, may be paid. And we ſhall cordially pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Examinant ſaith, That being with the King in his Privy-Chamber the day before the King departed from <hi>Breda,</hi> towards <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> being there alſo, the aforeſaid Capt. <hi>Briſco</hi> delivered the ſaid Memorial to the King, who laid it upon the Table; preſently upon this the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> came into the Privy Chamber where the King was, as aforeſaid, with the queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to whom the ſaid <hi>Briſco</hi> went, &amp; inform'd him that there were ſeveral Gentlemen ready to periſh, who had preſented a Petition to Secretary <hi>Lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> to be preſented to the King, and a Memorial delivered by the ſaid <hi>Briſco</hi> to the King in their behalf, which the King had laid on the Table, and had done nothing therin, &amp; deſired his Lordſhip to ſpeak to the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:171621:46"/> queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> to move the King in their behalf, who caſting his eye towards the Table, and the memorial that lay thereon, as this Examinant conceives, ſaid to the ſaid <hi>Briſco,</hi> as he ſaid to this Examinant, <hi>Well;</hi> and went to the queen of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> but what he ſaid to her, this Examinant knows not, nor had they any real effect of their deſires; only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Princeſs Royal, and the Governor of <hi>Breda,</hi> ten dayes after (upon this Examinants ſollicitation) diſcharged their quarters ſo far as one hundred Gilders came to; but ſaith, That what the Lord <hi>Craveu</hi> might ſay to the other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, or they to him before he came to the King, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or what he ſaid to them, or they to him after the ſaid Lord came from the King, this Examinant knowes not.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Edw. Drury.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VVHITE-HALL, <hi>June</hi> 10. 1652. <hi>The Depoſition of Captain</hi> John Briſco, <hi>aged about fourty years.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHo depoſeth, That at the time of the late Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between the King of Scots, and the Scotch Commiſſioners at <hi>Breda,</hi> he, this Deponent, with ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers of the late King, and the King of Scots being in great want, and having nothing to diſcharge their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, met together, and Major <hi>Rich. Fauconer,</hi> one of the ſaid Officers, as this Deponent conceives, drew a Petition in the Name of the ſaid Officers in Coll. <hi>Druries</hi> Lodgings, where the ſaid Officers were met, which was directed to the King to relieve them with ſome money; but this Deponent ſaith, That he being very lame of his wounds, tarried not to ſee the perfection thereof, &amp; therefore cannot further depoſe, as to any other contents of the Petition.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, That the ſaid Petition was put into the hands of Secretary <hi>Long,</hi> who told the Petitioner that nothing could be done in it till the Commiſſioners of Scotland had brought in ſome money to the King. He further depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:171621:47"/> That the ſaid Petitioners underſtanding that the King of Scots was to depart ſuddenly towards <hi>Scotland,</hi> they drew another Paper to remember the King of his Promiſe to Secretary <hi>Long,</hi> that the ſaid Petitioners ſhould have ſome relief; which memorial this Deponent ſaith he preſented to the King himſelf, his own condition being very ſad, who took it into his hand, and carryed it into the next Room, and put it down on the Board; this Deponent ſaith, That he went into the Room where the King was, and ſeeing the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> there, he, this Deponent, deſired the ſaid Lord to help the ſaid Deponent, and divers other Gentlemen in diſtreſs, who had preſented a Petition to the King for relief, and alſo a memorial to put them in mind of his promiſe to Secretary <hi>Long,</hi> that he would afford them ſome reliefe; whereupon the ſaid Lord ſaid, <hi>Well:</hi> The Deponent ſaith, That the queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was in the Room at the ſame time with the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> and the King, but whether the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> ſpake to the King, or to the queen of <hi>Boh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> this Deponent cannot ſay, but ſaith that Major <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> and Lievt. Coll. <hi>James Bardſey,</hi> were left by the ſaid Petitioners to wait on the King till he took water to ſee what might be done in point of relief; who ſent this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and the other Petitioners notice, That they could get no money. Afterwards the Governor of <hi>Breda</hi> did cauſe the ſaid quarters to be diſcharged.</p>
               <p>The Deponent further ſaith, That about twenty ſix Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers petitioned as aforeſaid, and that he, this Deponent had ſerved in the ſame Regiment under Sir <hi>Horat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Vere,</hi> with the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> in the Low Countryes, which was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherefore this Deponent ſpake to him to preſent the Petition as aforeſaid.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>JOHN BRISCO.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:171621:47"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
